Okay, good afternoon, sound check.
好的，下午好，声音检查。
Yep, we're good.
是的，我们是好的。
Okay, great,
好的，很好，
good evening, good morning, wherever you are,
晚上好，早上好，无论你在哪里，
so today I wanna talk about labs 2 a and b,
所以今天我想谈谈实验 2 a 和 b，
and this is really a question answering session,
这是一个问答环节，
so feel free to interrupt anytime,
所以你可以随时打断我，
ask questions as much as you like,
随便问问题，
it's really, today's lecture is really dedicated to your questions,
今天的课程是专门针对你们的问题的，
I summarized many of the questions,
我总结了许多问题，
that came up or either once or multiple times in the email,
在电子邮件中出现一次或多次，
on the right side here this on the board
在右边这块白板上，
and hopefully it will get through them as I walk through my solutions
希望当我演示我的解决方案时，能通过它们，
and so I'm gonna basically cover four topics related to the solution.
我将主要介绍与该解决方案相关的四个主题。
Ones we're going to first talk a little bit about voting, or like the voting code,
我们首先要谈一谈投票，或者投票代码，
basically the heartbeats,
然后是心跳，
yeah, and then I'll talk about start and commit.
然后我会讨论开始和提交。
This sort of follows I think there's suggestion that we made in the lab,
我认为这是我们在实验中提出的建议，
like how you should get started,
比如你应该如何开始，
like first voting to work,
第一次投票起作用，
you know they get heartbeats to work,
让心跳起作用，
once you got heartbeat to work,
一旦你的心跳开始工作，
you can actually start taking commands from clients
你可以开始接受来自客户端的命令，
and then of course yeah you gotta commit to supply them the applied channel.
然后当然你必须提交，
So there's roughly order planning go through,
所以有一个大致的方案顺序，
but again feel free to interrupt at any particular time.
但是，在任何时间，你都可以随意打断。
So before diving or looking at my particular solutions
所以在深入查看我的解决方案之前，
or the solutions I wrote this here,
或者我在这里写的解决方案，
I want to talk a little bit about debugging,
我想谈一谈调试，
because I was probably question that came up most in the, in all your in the submitted questions.
因为这是出现最多的问题，
Let me talk a little bit at a very high level about debugging,
让我在很高级别上谈一谈调试，
and this is a clearly a topic that we could spend a whole lecture on,
这显然是一个我们可以花上一整节课的话题，
and but I'm just gonna give you some of my high level approach,
但我只想给你们一些我的高级别的方法，
that you know I typically used to address,
我通常会用来解决，
you know to basically pass the labs.
通过实验。
And then basically starts out,
然后开始，
I just started started basically we're running the first test case,
我开始，我们运行的第一个测试用例，
and of course if I have not written any code,
当然，如果我没有写过任何代码，
I'm gonna fail it,
我会失败，
but at least I have some starting point,
但至少我有了一个起点，
where I can I can start writing some code for
我可以开始写一些代码，
and so you know think about the first test case,
所以想想第一个测试用例，
you know starting writing,
开始编写，
look at the hints and write some code,
查看提示并编写一些代码，
and while writing the code,
在编写代码时，
yeah, I find it you know convenient,
我觉得这很方便，
in this lab to or the sets of labs,
在这个实验或这个实验集合中，
actually any lab in the 6.824,
实际上， 6.824 中的任何实验，
to log all messages,
要记录所有消息，
and you know typically use a DPrintf function in [] Go
通常使用 util.go 中的 DPrintf 函数，
and I'm pretty systematic of logging messages.
我很有系统地记录消息，
And the reason that I do this isn't for debugging purposes,
我这样做的原因不是为了调试目的，
and so I'll write code,
所以，我将编写代码，
run the test code fails,
运行测试代码失败，
write some code to actually try to pass the test case
编写一些代码以尝试通过测试用例，
and you know there's two scenarios,
这里有两种情况，
you know one you know I pass,
一个是我通过了，
which then I immediately move on to the next test case,
然后我立即转到下一个测试用例，
or I fail,
或者我失败了，
and in that case,
在这种情况下，
the first thing I do is
我做的第一件事是，
to study the test case a little bit more in detail
更详细地研究测试用例，
and try to figure out what actually the test case is trying to test
并尝试找出测试用例要测试的东西，
and you know the name of the test cases often very suggestive of what the particular scenario
测试用例的名称
or what sort of set of scenarios a testcase is trying to cover
或者测试用例试图涵盖的场景集合，
and then I tried to answer the formulate for myself,
然后我试着自己回答，
and hypothesis not why you my code why not you know test that pass the test case,
假设为什么我的代码，
and so basically this is sort of a moment of reflection and thinking,
所以这是一个反思和思考的时刻，
and, to sort of like you understand
而且，为了理解，
what the constructing my head a scenario,
我脑子里想的是什么场景，
that there seems to fit the test case,
似乎符合测试用例，
you know, think about my code what actually it could be a problem
想想我的代码，
and once I have a hypothesis,
一旦我有了一个假设，
then the next thing to do is like study,
然后接下来要做的就是学习，
you know basically try to confirm the hypothesis,
试着确认这个假设，
whether my explanation for why I'm passing the test case, might be right or wrong,
我的解释，为什么通过测试，可能是对的或错的，
and so to do that,
所以，要做到这一点，
then basically I study the log,
我要研究一下日志，
so if I have a print you know and trace of all the messages,
所以如果我有打印或所有消息，
being sent to the part of the protocol,
发送到协议的那部分，
I can look at that you know trace
我可以看到跟踪，
and you know to see you know where things go wrong
看看哪里出了问题，
and sort of work where backwards
工作回退，
and you know in that way, sort of test and refine my hypothesis about why my code might be wrong,
使用这种方式，
sometimes you know that may require you know going back
有时这可能需要回到过去，
and basically run the test case test to basically get more detailed log output,
运行测试用例测试以获得更详细的日志输出，
although early on I tend to be very systematic,
虽然在早期我倾向于非常系统化，
and you don't really have to add any print statements,
你不需要添加任何打印语句，
but in some cases not necessary,
但在某些情况下，是需要的，
then you know that gives me more information
那么这给了我更多的信息，
and I can sort of really zoom in on scenario, that you know my code doesn't handle,
我可以真正放大场景，
once I sort of have a hypothesis,
一旦我有了一个假设，
I verified with the log,
我在日志里检查，
that they are indeed the hypothesis seems to be correct,
这个假设似乎是正确的，
and that is a source or a bug in my code,
这是我的代码中的一个 bug ，
I can just go fix the code,
我可以修改代码，
and then run the test case.
然后运行测试用例。
And so this is a brief process,
所以这是一个简短的过程，
run test case, if fail, study test case and study logs to formulate hypothesis,
运行测试用例，
you know trying to confirm that hypothesis
试图证实这一假设，
and then move on fix the code
然后继续修复代码，
and then move onto the next one
然后转到下一个，
and that tend to be reasonable systematic in this.
这往往是合理的，系统的。
And so for example often I'll actually write down in a some file, a text file,
例如，我经常会在某个文件中写下，一个文本文件，
what my hypothesis is
我的假设是什么，
and sort of trying to collect evidence or counter evidence,
并试图收集证据或反证据，
you know to need to prove or disprove my hypothesis,
要证明或反驳我的假设，
I really have a good reason to fix the code,
我有很好的理由来修复代码，
I think you know any approach that basically it's not very systematic,
我认为任何方法都不是非常系统化的，
for example you think something is not really a hundred percent right,
例如，你认为有些事情并不是百分之百正确的，
you know maybe change that
也许可以改变这个，
and see if you pass the test cases,
看看你是否通过了测试用例，
tends to be not work that well,
往往效果不是很好，
I think that takes a lot of time,
我认为这需要很长时间，
because you might be wrong
因为你可能错了，
or and worse you might be wrong and actually pass the test case and think you're right,
或者更糟糕的是，你可能是错的，
but it turned out like basically you're just shifting the bug from one corner to another corner
但事实证明，
and it will show up later again.
它将在稍后再次出现。
So at a very high-level, this is the approach, that I take,
所以在非常高级别上，这是我采取的方法，
and you can see what the the key here is really logging the messages.
你可以看到这里的关键是记录消息。
Any questions or comments on this, this approach,
对这个方法，有什么疑问或者评论，
I know it's a very high level,
我知道这是很高的级别上，
but at least give you some sense about how I approach this.
但至少让你对我是如何处理这件事有所了解。
So the messages here are the RPC.
所以这里的消息是 RPC ？
Yes, all the RPCs.
是的，所有的 RPC 。
Okay, okay.
好的，好的。
Okay, so some, so.
好的，所以有一些，所以。
I have a quick question,
我有一个简短的问题，
so what's a good like approach
那么什么是好的方法，
for deciding the granularity of what to log and what not to log.
用于决定记录什么和不记录什么的粒度？
Ah, that's a very good, exact great question,
啊，这是一个非常好的问题，
I was hoping that someone has asked,
我希望有人提问，
I tend to be log things are pretty fine-grained,
我倾向于把事情做得很细粒度，
[] log everything,
[]记录所有东西，
and, then, I use you know whatever I pulled you know basically the log in an editor
然后，我使用，
or use Unix utilities like grep to basically pull out the things
或者使用像 grep 这样的 Unix 程序，
And the reason I'm doing that is,
我这么做的原因是，
you know sometimes I don't know what level granularity I want to study something
有时候我不知道我想要研究什么粒度的东西，
and I want to go back and run the test again,
我不想回去再做一次测试，
I just collect everything,
我只是收集所有的东西，
and then you know filter stuff out, that I know that I care about.
然后找出我关心的东西。
And this brings me on,
这让我开始了，
so, some people write quite a bit of infrastructure for debugging,
所以，有些人编写了相当多的调试基础设施，
using the logs, making a lot more easier to understand,
使用日志，使更容易理解，
I'm pretty primitive, you know DPrintf and lots of information,
我很原始， DPrintf 和信息日志，
although the I I structure my printf in a clear manner,
尽管我以清晰的方式组织我的 printf ，
so I can see what the source,
这样我就能看到来源是什么，目的地是什么，
and what the the RPC itself is
以及 RPC 本身是什么，
and so I can sort of figure grabbed filter very quickly,
我可以非常快速地找出过滤，
because all the text lines have a particular format.
因为所有文本行都有特定的格式。
Some people spend quite a bit of time building some infrastructure to make it all easier,
一些人花了相当多的时间建设一些基础设施，
take over one of the TAs Jose,
TA 之一的 Jose ，
when he took the class,
当他上课的时候，
he actually built some software to make it a little bit of Python script
他构建了一些软件，
and I thought it might be interesting to see what he did,
我想看看他所做的会很有趣，
I'm gonna stop sharing
我要停止分享，
and then ask Jose to share and maybe demo
然后请 Jose 分享，也许还有 demo ，
like how his log structure works.
它的日志结构是如何工作的。
Sorry, I have a follow-up question.
抱歉，我有一个跟进的问题。
So how do you make the debugging prints going to a log rather than the standard out.
那么，如何将调试 print 写入日志而不是标准输出？
Oh, usually [] than to and output to a file, so.
哦，通常是输出到一个文件，所以。
So you just pipe everything into a file.
所以，你只是使用管道将所有东西到一个文件中。
Yes, I pipe it to a file.
是的，我把它通过管道传输到一个文件中。
Got it, thank you.
知道了，谢谢。
So I guess this Johe's screen and Jose go ahead.
我想这是 Jose 的屏幕， Jose 继续。
You can hear me again.
你能听到我说话吗？
Yeah, I can hear you.
是的，我能听到。
Okay awesome,
好的，太棒了，
and as I kind of agree on a bunch of points,
我同意这些观点，
I mean things very similar to like how Frans was describing,
事情与 Frans 所描述的很像，
pretty aggressive loggers I try to kind of,
[]日志，我试着去做，
and again I also have a format that I follow
我也有一个我遵循的格式，
and then I'm gonna show is kind of how went about
然后我要展示的是，
making my life easier going and passing through the logs.
让我的生活更轻松，并通过日志。
The high-level idea is I do very simple structure in Go,
高级别的想法是我在 Go 中做非常简单的结构，
and then I usually dump that the standard out out to a file,
然后我会把这些标准输入转存到一个文件中，
and then I use Python scripts to actually do the,
然后我使用 Python 脚本执行，
kind of like all the coloring and structuring,
所有的颜色和结构，
since that's much easier to do in Python than that in Go.
因为这在 Python 中要比在 Go 中容易得多。
And so here's for example when I get out of whenever a test in Go,
例如，这是我在一个 Go 测试中得到的，
so when I enable the VERBOSE,
当我启用 VERBOSE 时，
I just get like an output that looks something like this,
我得到一个输出，看起来像这样，
and here what I'm logging is,
我在这里记录的是，
kind of like the number of milliseconds is the first column
毫秒数是第一列，
and that's pretty useful when you're trying to debug timer events,
当你调试计时器事件时，这非常有用，
things like that are trying to see how long an RPC takes to fail,
诸如此类的事情，
then the second column is what I would like to call topics,
第二栏是我称为主题，
they're not levels, because they are you know there's no hierarchy between
它们不是级别，
and they're just related to different events in raft,
它们只是与 Raft 上的不同时间有关，
probably a lot of you right now have realized that in lab 3,
可能你们中的许多人现在已经意识到，
like timers, there's elections, there's like log, things being applied communication with a state machine,
比如定时器，选举，日志，
and all of those events happen with slightly different frequencies,
所有这些事件发生的频率都略有不同，
so if you want to later, like select some of them
所以如果你想之后从它们中选择，
or like decide to ignore the more most ones,
或者决定忽略更多的那些，
it's really handy to just have like that, that category,
这样的类别真的很方便，
and then the third column probably a lot of you have something,
然后第三列，可能你们中的许多人有这个，
because we thought that is pretty hard to reason about what is going on,
因为我们认为这很难对发生的事情进行推理，
and the rest is just a free form message,
剩下的是一条自由形式的信息，
that explains kind of like what this message is about
解释了这条信息是关于什么的，
and even though this is kind of just the very initial test that you run,
尽管这只是你运行的最初始的测试，
the one that just passed, that you can do an election,
刚刚通过的，你可以进行选举的那个，
you have to like read, follow what the logic is going on here.
你必须阅读，遵循这里的逻辑。
So the way I made this easier kind of like first approach
所以我让这件事变得更容易，
and this is what I did when I took the class,
这就是我在课程中所做的，
was just convert all the topics into colors,
把所有的主题都转换成颜色，
like most more internal support wide array of color support
像大多数内部支持一样，广泛的颜色支持，
and again by doing this in Python,
同样，通过使用 Python 语言做这个，
you can use some fantastic libraries that do all the heavy lifting,
你可以使用一些出色的库来完成所有繁重的任务，
so you don't have to get in the in the [] of doing this.
你不必参与到这件事中来。
And here yes have included different events with different colors
在这里，是的，包括了不同颜色的不同事件，
and as you get more familiar with the colors,
随着你对颜色越来越熟悉，
for example here all the timers events are in gray,
例如，这里所有定时器事件都是灰色的，
so maybe they're easier to ignore
所以也许它们更容易被忽视，
or we're looking for when someone is voting,
或者我们寻找当有人投票的时候，
we can look at like [], which relate to vote,
我们可以看一下青色，它与投票有关，
and that like we'll just encode visually things are much easier to pick up,
我们在视觉上编码，东西更容易找出来，
for example here yellow is when we elect, elect a new leader.
例如，这里的黄色是我们选举，选举新领导人的时候。
We still have to decide who is saying what,
我们还得决定谁在说什么，
and in order to do that,
为了做到这一点，
what I incorporated just having different columns,
我加入了不同的列，
and again what I'm doing is just running here,
再说一次，我现在所做的就是运行，
what I'm doing just running the standard test script
我所做的只是运行标准测试脚本，
and then just piping that into like the the script I wrote,
然后通过管道到我写的脚本中，
in this case, I'm specifying that I have three columns,
在本例中，我指定我有三列，
because of like three peers in this test case
因为在这个测试用例中有三个节点，
and I have now decided to ignore the timer,
我现在决定忽略计时器，
like the events with the timer [topic],
就像定时器主题的事件，
because there are too many of them
因为它们太多了，
and if timing logic is working,
并且如果定时逻辑工作了，
we probably don't need them to the debug what's going on
我们可能不需要它们来调试正在发生的事情，
and if you look at this log
如果你看一下这个日志，
compared to what we the plaintext log
与我们的明文日志相比，
is fairly easy to see, that what's going on,
很容易看到，发生了什么，
it's like three servers are starting,
有三台服务器在启动，
the last one is becoming a candidate,
最后一个成为候选者，
the other two are voting for that,
另外两个给它投了票，
it's becoming a leader as soon as it gets the first vote
一旦获得第一票，它就会成为领导者，
and then it just heartbeats through the rest of the test,
然后它就会在剩下的测试中心跳，
and there's nothing else to look at it.
没有其他东西可以看了。
But now again compared to this,
但现在再一次和这个相比，
it's kind of like an order of magnitude easier to pick up what is going on
更容易发现正在发生的事情，
and as you tweak that to your liking,
当你根据自己的喜好调整它的时候，
it becomes more and more efficient.
它变得越来越高效。
And as you move to like harder test,
当你转向更难的测试时，
because a lot of you have probably have had to look at the logs of the backup test in the 2B lab,
因为你们中的许多人可能
there will be lots and lots of events going on
会有很多很多的事件在进行，
and even if you know what you need,
即使你知道你需要什么，
it might become like a daunting task,
这可能会成为一项艰巨的任务，
going through like thousands of lines of logs,
通过上千行的日志，
you're searching for the point of failure
你寻找失败点，
and trying to reason about what's going on.
并试图对发生的事情进行推理。
Again, if we look, just like make this a kind of a similar format to visualize,
同样，如果我们查看，
we can quickly see what's going on,
我们可以很快看到发生了什么，
we just have like five different servers, that are starting,
我们有五个不同的服务器正在启动，
the first one is becoming a candidate,
第一个成为候选者，
the other ones are voting for it,
其他人投票给它，
becoming a leader
成为领导者，
and by looking at the different columns,
通过观察不同的列，
we can see, for example all,
我们可以看到，
so we can see that a new entry is received,
所以我们可以看到收到了一个新条目，
and this, this servers are receiving
这个服务器正在接收，
and because backup to have a very verbose log,
而且由于 backup 具有非常详细的日志，
I have a lot of drop RPCs,
我有很多 Drop RPC ，
I'm also ignoring those topics here
我在这里也忽略了这些话题，
and as the test goes on,
随着测试的进行，
we can start reasoning about what's going on,
我们可以开始对发生的事情进行推理，
so so fairly helpful to just have like some print statements or like the bug segment in the test code,
所以，可能是有帮助的，
you just can modify there,
你可以在那里修改，
to know what the test is doing,
知道测试在做什么，
for example here the test detects that the first server S0 is the leader
例如，在这里，测试检测到，
and then this connects S2 to S4,
然后断开 S2 直到 S4 的连接，
which are like the three on the right side
就是右边的三个，
and that's pretty much what happens,
这几乎就是发生的事情，
we just get a stream of entries, that won't be committed,
我们收到一串条目，不会被提交，
because there's only two servers that can talk to each other
因为只有两台服务器可以相互通信，
and then after a while,
然后过了一段时间，
we see that the first two are now disconnected
我们看到前两个现在是断开的，
and the three on the right are reconnected
右边的三个重新连接在一起，
and now they can form a majority,
现在它们可以形成大多数，
and that's what we will see,
这就是我们将看到的，
like the last one becomes a candidate, achieves a majority
最后一个人成为候选者，获得多数，
and kind of repeatedly we see the color pattern of like green and purple,
我们可以重复地看到绿色和紫色的颜色模式，
like this staircase signifying that oh yeah receiving an entry
就像这个楼梯表示，哦，接受一个条目，
and propagating it through the other servers
并将它传播到其他服务器，
and the disconnected servers here converting to a candidate.
而这里的断开连接的服务器转换为候选者。
And hopefully I've convinced you by now,
希望我现在已经说服了你，
by there's slightly changing the presentation of your logs,
通过稍微改变日志的呈现方式，
kind of like the mental effort to like go through them can significantly decrease,
经历它们的精神努力会显著减少，
and even though this is really fancy,
尽管这真的很花哨，
there's not a lot of like fancy code,
没有太多花哨的代码，
going on I just use some of the self python libraries, mainly rich,
我只使用了一些自带的 Python 库，主要是 rich ，
and kind of all fits in about like a hundred lines of Python script,
大概有上百行的 Python 脚本，
and if you're interested,
如果你感兴趣的话，
I wrote a blog post, that will be linking on the web site on piazza
我写了一篇博客文章，
about kind of like the these steps to build a tool like this,
关于构建一个这样的工具的步骤，
and you know how it all fit together,
这些是如何结合在一起的，
like some like design decisions related to that.
一些与此相关的设计决定。
And if anyone has any questions specific to this, happy to answer them.
如果任何人有任何与此相关的问题，很乐意回答。
Any questions for Jose?
有什么问题要问 Jose 吗？
Yeah, I have a question more about general logging,
是的，我有一个关于一般日志的问题，
so I know that I had some bugs,
所以我知道有一些 bug ，
that when I put in the logging they were no longer there,
当我把它们放进日志时，它们已经不在那里了，
because of some timing issue, or perhaps a concurrency issue,
由于某些时间问题，或者可能是并发问题，
so what, what do we do then.
那么我们该怎么办？
Okay, so there's a couple things I do,
好的，我做了几件事，
first of all, one reason I log, it's sort of a fine-grained,
首先，我记录细粒度的一个原因，
always at the same level of granularity and fine granularity,
始终保持细粒度，
so I always have a trace with everything
所以我总是对每件事都有跟踪，
and I generally don't have to go back.
我一般都不需要回去。
The other thing to do is,
另一件要做的事情是，
I do run the test many many times
我确实做了很多很多次测试，
and they save all logs,
保存所有的日志，
and then once I hit the wrong one,
一旦我遇到了错误的，
once I hit a bug,
一旦我碰到了 bug ，
then you know I really studied that particular log.
那么我研究那个特定的日志。
And so, for example if I run something overnight,
所以，比如，如果我连夜运行一些东西，
I just save all the logs from all the runs overnight
我只是保存连夜运行的所有日志，
and then grab the one in your field.
然后找出失败的那个。
Anybody have any further questions on the topic of logging?
对于日志的话题，还有更多问题吗？
Okay good, let me proceed,
好的，让我继续，
before again, you know look at your code I want to talk a little bit about the structure,
在之前的，看看代码，
that my particular solution has
我的解决方案有的，
and this is definitely not the only structure,
这绝对不是唯一的结构，
you can do it in many many different ways
你可以用很多不同的方法来做这件事，
and you're you're free to actually do it in many different ways
你可以自由地以多种不同的方式做这件事，
and the fact that every year when I teach class,
事实上，每年我上课的时候，
I I actually try to rewrite,
我试着重写，
implement the labs again
再次实现实验，
and often experiment with different types of ways of implementing it.
并经常尝试不同类型的实现方式。
So the one I'll show you with you today is
所以今天我要向你们展示的是，
one that I wrote over [],
一个我写的[]，
you know sort of getting ready for 6.824
是为 6.824 做准备的，
and then it has the following structure,
然后它有如下的结构。
it's a pretty standard structure,
这是一个非常标准的结构，
you know, let me draw a box,
让我画一个盒子，
you know signifying the raft library,
表示 Raft 库，
you know there's two basically API calls,
有两个 API 调用，
[] one Start, to sort of initiate, and append entries
一个是 Start ，用来初始化追加条目，
and to initiate a logging operation in one to actually and output,
初始化日志操作，
then, in you know one documentation we're showing,
然后，在我们展示的一个文件中，
how basically one, essentially one structure, the raft structure,
基本上是一个 Raft 结构，
that basically has all the state of the of the raft library,
它具有 Raft 库的所有状态，
you know all the variables that are in the figure two
图 2 中的所有变量，
and basically have one lock on this guy,
这个有一个锁，
and, basically all my, so I use quite coarse-grained locking all my RPC handlers,
基本上我所有的，
all my start,
我一开始，
take basically just one lock,
只使用一个锁，
do whatever stuff they need to do,
做它们需要做的任何事情，
do and then release the lock,
然后释放锁，
so there's a couple threads, you know that sort of running around,
所以有几个线程，在各处运行，
one of course is the ticker threads,
其中一个当然定时器线程，
that we sort of gave you,
我们给你的，
and you know that just wait,
它只是等待，
I'll show you in a second,
我稍后向你们展示，
that will wait for some number of milliseconds, you know 50 milliseconds
它将等待一定的毫秒数， 50 毫秒，
and then run and then check periodically,
然后运行，然后定期检查，
if any timeout, election timeout has gone off
如果有任何超时，选举超时已经结束，
and does whatever needs to be done,
做任何需要做的事情，
I have one thread dedicated to writing on the apply channel,
我有一个线程专门用于在 apply 通道上写入数据，
so no other thread actually writes to the apply channel,
没有其他线程写入 apply 通道，
there's only a single one
只有一个，
and it basically sleeps on a condition variable,
它在一个条件变量上睡眠，
and so when for example a new append entry comes in from the leader
当一个新的附加条目从领导者处进入时，
and the commit index goes up,
然后提交索引会增加，
then the thread that thread will wake up on the signal
然后线程将在信号上被唤醒，
and the condition variable that will wake up the thread
条件变量将唤醒那个线程，
that actually looks at the apply
它写入 apply 通道，
it will grab whatever you know entries out of the log,
它将从日志中获取条目，
and stick them on the apply channel.
并把它们放在 apply 通道上。
And, so that's one reason,
所以，这是一个原因，
a single thread is that of course you can't hold locks while writing across the apply channel,
单个线程当然不能持有锁，
but at least you might get a [cause] problems later,
你稍后可能会遇到问题，
and so I just have a single thread,
所以我只有一个线程，
that actually writes on the apply channel.
它在 apply 通道上写入。
Then, the, of course you know number of things coming in from the outside,
然后，当然有很多东西是从外面进来的，
you know require messages coming in
需要传入的消息，
and of course each message, or each RPC starts its own thread,
当然，每个消息或每个 RPC 都会启动自己的线程，
like Go well RPC library will basically start a thread for every incoming message
RPC 库会为每条传入消息启动一个线程，
and basically the way I process every incoming messages,
我处理每一条消息的方式，
the first thing that grabs the log on the raft structure,
第一件事抓住 Raft 结构的日志，
it reads writes you know the raft structure,
它读写 Raft 结构，
and then when it's done,
然后当它完成的时候，
you have releases the lock, maybe lock,
你可以解锁，
and maybe in between, it will update you know signal in the condition variable, too.
也许在这两者之间，
Then, of course start itself,
然后，当然 Start 自己，
you know runs on a particular thread,
在特定的线程上运行，
so it jumps into the raft library,
所以它跳入 Raft 库，
you know that's the same thing,
这是一回事，
you know acquire lock and then,
获取锁，然后，
let me append entry,
让我添加条目，
if the leader appended to the log
如果领导者追加到日志结构中，
and since I want to do the append RPC in parallel,
因为我想并行执行附加 RPC ，
basically what the way it works is,
它的工作方式是，
that you know for every RPC,
对于每个 RPC ，
I start a separate thread,
我开始一个单独的线程，
and that are in that thread, actually is responsible for sending it,
而在那个线程中上负责发送它，
reserving the response and in the response you know doing any updating,
保留响应，并在响应中进行任何更新，
that is necessary to their [] structure,
对 Raft 结构是必要的。
so response handler when the response comes in,
所以，响应处理程序在响应到达时，
you know grab the raft lock
获取 Raft 锁，
and then do whatever update necessary to the raft state
然后更新任何需要的 Raft 状态，
and then release the lock.
然后释放锁。
So, so there's a bunch of threads,
所以，这里有一堆线程，
quite a number of threads you can be running around,
你可以运行相当多的线程，
because their messages may be late,
因为一些消息可能会迟到，
you know and so there may be many, many, many threads here,
所以这里可能有很多的线程，
and, there might be multiple Starts,
而且可能会有多个 Start ，
there might be a Start outstanding is,
可能会有 Start 是，
instead of maybe multiple threads there,
而不是那里的多个线程，
and of course your ticker, you also start, may send heartbeats
当然，你的定时器也开始了，可能会发出心跳，
and those heartbeats you know again turn into a separate thread,
那些心跳又变成了一个单独的线程，
but all those threads are basically serialized by the raft lock
但所有这些线程都是由 Raft 锁序列化的，
or by raft lock serialize.
或通过 Raft 锁串行化。
And so when I print, print long messages,
所以当我打印日志消息时，
you know, of course this inside you know done while holding the raft lock,
当然这是在持有 Raft 锁时做的，
and since you know sort of every thread runs one by one,
因为每个线程都是一个接一个地运行，
you know a lot of messages would make a lot of sense,
很多信息都很有意义，
you know they they all serialized too.
它们也是串行化的。
Similar I make all RPC handlers atomic or serialized,
类似地，我使所有 RPC 处理程序都是原子的或序列化的，
so you know fine-grained locking,
所以细粒度锁，
and that helps and I'll talk about in a second
这很有帮助，我稍后会谈到，
and then the only thing that you have to be little bit careful with,
然后，你唯一要小心的是，
if you do sort of coarse-grained locking,
如果你执行某种粗粒度锁，
is that now you can get into deadlocks,
你可能陷入死锁，
in particular, you can have deadlock if you hold locks across RPCs
特别是可能会出现死锁，
and so I never hold no locks across RPCs,
所以我从来不会在 RPC 上持有锁，
and that partially achieved,
而这部分实现了，
your as achieved as a side effect of really starting a new thread for every RPC.
作为一个连带效果，
So that's sort of the overall structure,
这就是整体结构，
also by this particular solution, that I'll share in a second with you,
还有这个解决方案，
again, other structures are possible,
同样，其他结构也是可能的，
but hopefully this gives you some, some ideas,
但希望这能给你一些想法，
any questions about this?
对此有什么问题吗？
What were the threads on the right?
右边的线程是什么？
On the right, these guys?
右边的这些？
Yeah.
是的。
Those are the incoming messages,
这些是传入的消息，
so like append RPC,
比如，附加 RPC ，
for append RPC request or vote request,
附加 RPC 请求或投票请求，
I think the only two.
我想只有两个。
I also have a question,
我也有一个问题，
what's the, is there a benefit of having a single thread sleeping on the condition variable,
什么是，
and then having only that thread,
然后只有那个线程，
a thread sending to apply channel,
一个程发送到 apply 通道，
compared to having each RPC thread send to the apply channel.
与让每个 RPC 线程发送到 apply 通道相比。
Well, everything has to go in order on the apply channel, correct,
好的， apply 通道的所有东西都要有序，
so the whole log that you made,
所以你做的整个日志，
that's in the raft structure has to be sent on the apply channel,
在 Raft 结构中，必须在 apply 通道上发送，
exactly in order as the entries are in the log,
完全按照日志中条目的顺序，
and so that's just more easier to do,
所以这更容易做到，
I find it easy to do with the single thread,
我发现用单个线程很容易做到，
because that basically goes through the raft log
因为这要经过 Raft 日志，
and there's sticks from one by one, the entries onto the apply channel,
把条目一个一个地放入 apply 通道，
and there's no sort of coordination necessary.
而且没有必要进行任何协调。
That makes sense, okay.
理解了，好的。
Yeah, so like we all you know,
好的，像我们大家都知道的，
yeah, so this goes like up into the servers that actually uses the raft library.
是的，这是进入了实际使用 Raft 库的服务器。
Okay, so one more word about about sort of fine-grained versus coarse-grained,
好的，再多说一句细粒度与粗粒度的对比，
some of you, it's a common mistake early on,
你们中的一些人，这在早期是一个常见的错误，
when you haven't done that much you know [] programming,
当你还没做那么多并行编程，
you might do, if you have your RPC struct,
你可能会做，如果你有自己的 RPC 结构，
you know maybe you have like the log and some other fields,
也许你有像日志和其他一些字段，
and some people or sometimes you know there's a [temptation] or not unreasonable to have multiple locks,
有些人，或者有时，这里有[]，
so instead of having a single lock or even have a single one,
所以，不是只有一个锁，
but not really hold it for a long time.
但并不是持有很长时间。
And, and I think in general minds reasoning about the code a little bit hard,
而且，我认为在一般情况下，
so for example common thing that you know you might do,
例如，你可能会做的常见事情，
then it's like if you have an RPC handler,
如果你有一个 RPC 处理程序，
like this some Request handler, you know whatever args reply,
比如这个 Request 处理程序，包括 Args Reply ，
just sketching this out,
只是勾勒出这个，
you know you might know something,
你可能会做 mu.lock ，
do something you know with arguments,
和参数一起执行，
maybe you know updates some state you know in the raft structure
也许更新 Raft 结构中的一些状态，
and to mu.unlock,
并执行 mu.unlock ，
then maybe do some other stuff,
然后也许做一些其他的事情，
there's not maybe directly related to the raft structure,
可能与 Raft 结构没有直接关系，
and then basically maybe grab the lock again,
然后可能会再次获取锁，
and then you know whatever update and read maybe to raft structure again
然后再次更新或读取 Raft 结构，
and then unlock
然后解锁，
and all you're sort of in a single RPC handler.
所有这些都在一个 RPC 处理程序中。
And, just as a thought exercise,
作为一种思维练习，
what is risky about this sort of style of fine-grained locking.
这种细粒度锁的风格有什么风险？
I know this is a bit artificial,
我知道这有点做作，
but it is a reasonable common,
但这是一种合理的普遍现象，
sort of early mistake that you know you might make.
一种你可能会犯的早期错误。
You have to like recheck your assumptions before locking again every time, right.
你必须重新检查你的设置，
Yeah, you know basically this executes atomically,
是的，上这是原子执行的，
this executes it atomically,
这是原子执行的，
but lots of things can happen in between, right,
但中间可能会发生很多事情，
so for example new RPCs might have been coming in,
例如，新的 RPC 可能进来，
and they might be running too,
它们可能也在运行，
and they might actually have been updating the raft struct or raft state
它们可能更新了 Raft 结构或 Raft 状态，
between these two critical sections,
在这两个关键部分之间，
between one and two,
在一和二之间，
and so by the time you know to the,
所以这时，
you start running critical section 2,
你开始运行关键部分 2 ，
raft structure might be completely different,
Raft 结构可能是完全不同的，
and have might completely different content,
可能有完全不同的内容，
and, so to avoid you know those kind of situations,
所以，为了避免这种情况，
you know my general approach is to basically,
我一般的做法是，
you know basically have is to be one critical, one critical section,
有一个关键的部分，
so I don't have to recheck any,
所以我不需要重新检查任何东西，
I don't have to recheck the state at the new one,
我不需要在新的重新检查状态，
the second critical section starts.
在第二个关键部分开始时。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
This problem shows up in different you know,
这个问题表现在不同的方面，
or this problem can show up in a different fashion, in different ways,
或者这个问题可以以不同的方式表现出来，
but instead of [] problems, always the same,
但问题总是一样，
if you do a lot of fine-grained locking,
如果你执行大量细粒度锁，
you're going to have additional interleavings
你将会有额外的交错，
and you have to consider and make sure that you don't have a incorrect interleavings will result in incorrect behavior.
你必须考虑并确保，
I want to ask,
我想问一下，
is it but it's not possible to avoid rechecking conditions,
是不是无法避免复查条件，
after you send an RPC thread, inside the RBC thread.
在你在 RPC 线程中时。
Yeah, you, you cannot hold a lock while sending, right,
是的，你不能在发送时持有锁，
so you should not you know,
所以你不应该，
here you should not call whatever you know send RPC,
在这里，你不应调用发送 RPC ，
because you can't do that while holding a lock,
因为当你拿着锁的时候你不能这样做，
because they can easily result in deadlock
因为它们很容易导致死锁，
or you're holding a lock,
或者你持有一把锁，
you sent it to a peer in RPC while still holding the lock,
你在仍持有锁的情况下，通过 RPC 发送到一个节点，
the peer actually sends RPC to you,
那个节点发送 RPC 给你，
but you're holding you know,
但你持有，
that you're the leader already holds the lock and the [] structure,
你是领导者已经持有了锁和[]结构，
so the response cannot be process
所以响应不能被处理，
and maybe you know the two are interdependent
也许这两者是相互依存的，
and may you have a deadlock.
你可能会陷入死锁。
One thing that's worth noting is,
值得注意的一件事是，
something I saw some people doing is that,
我看到一些人在做的事情是，
they spin off a thread to send an RPC,
它们启动一个线程来发送 RPC ，
in that thread, they take the lock to prepare the arguments for the RPC
在那个线程中，它们获取锁来为 RPC 准备参数，
and then they send the RPC without lock,
然后他们不加锁地发送 RPC ，
and you can do that,
你可以做这个，
but it's often a fewer interleavings,
但它通常是较少的交错，
if you generate the arguments for the RPC,
如果为 RPC 生成参数，
before you [spit] off the thread,
在你启动线程之前，
that actually sends it.
它发送的。
Good point, we'll see, we'll show, this will show up in a second,
说得好，我们会看到，我们在稍后展示，
actually in.
事实上在。
But doesn't that cause,
但这不是导致，
so sometimes it's actually depending on the implementation,
所以，有时它取决于实现，
I think it's beneficial for other RPCs to see the changes,
我认为让其他 RPC 看到这些变化是有益的，
like for example if other RPCs made progress you want to start off
例如，如果其他 RPC 取得了进展，
Perhaps, yeah it depends on exactly what you do,
可能是，这取决于你到底做了什么，
like how your implementation works,
比如你的实现是如何工作的，
I I don't do that,
我不会那么做，
at least, I don't think I do what you're suggesting,
至少，我不认为我做了你建议的事，
when I send an RPC to all the peers,
当我向所有节点发送 RPC 时，
all the peers are going to get exactly the same arguments,
所有的节点都会得到相同的参数，
and no change in between.
在这两者之间没有变化。
Okay, so okay, let me then talk a little bit about the implementation,
好的，好的，让我来谈一谈实现的问题，
can people read, can people read the screen?
大家能看到屏幕吗？
Sorry, I have a follow question.
抱歉，我有一个跟进的问题。
Yeah.
嗯。
So I think you mentioned that we shouldn't lock around sending things over the apply channel.
所以我想你提到过，
Yes, although let me,
是的，尽管，让我，
yeah, it's risky,
是的，这很冒险，
because while you're holding the lock, right,
因为当你持有锁的时候，
you send on the apply channel,
你发送到 apply 通道，
you might also block sitting on the apply channel,
你也可能阻塞在 apply 通道上，
because the servers you know most the other side must be reading, correct,
因为另一端必须读取，
before you're unlock,
在你解锁之前，
of course, you have buffered and buffered,
当然，你有缓冲，
let's say we have a lot of buffer channel,
假设我们有没有缓冲的通道，
but just an unbuffered channel,
只是一个无缓冲的通道，
and so the reader, if there's no reader,
所以读取者，如果没有读取者，
then this writer will block,
那么这个写入者就会阻塞，
and maybe holding the lock
也许还会持有锁，
and that might be you know mainly to problems later
这可能会导致后面的问题，
and lead to deadlocks.
并导致死锁。
[] on that, isn't this all right,
在那上面，这不对吗，
like like the apply channel will never,
apply 通道永远不会，
like the client who's calling raft,
比如调用 Raft 的客户端，
well [never] would hold the lock, right, they're like.
永远不会持有锁，它们是。
You don't, not not true,
你不是，不是真的，
here's are sort of servers quick sitting on top,
这是一种位于顶部的服务器，
calling start and reading from the apply channel,
调用 Start ，并从 apply 通道读取，
but it's called start,
但它调用 Start ，
start is you know depending on how you do it,
Start 取决于你如何做到它，
you start as a thread
你从一个线程开始，
and jumps into with that thread into the raft library
然后在那个线程进入 Raft 库，
and at least in my implementation,
至少在我的实现中，
the first thing that start function does is actually wrap the raft lock,
Start 函数所做的第一件事是，
and it can't grab the lock, raft lock,
它不能获取 Raft 锁，
is actually either the apply thread is already holding it,
要么是 apply 线程已经持有它，
trying to get something on the apply channel,
想要在 apply 通道上获取一些东西，
but the servers now won't read from the apply channel,
但服务器现在不会从 apply 通道读取，
depending on how you set it up,
取决于你如何设置它，
but as you're saying that,
但正如你所说的，
there is a risk here,
这其中存在风险，
you've got to be a little careful.
你得小心一点。
So would the solution be just to like create a new thread.
那么，解决方案是不是创建一个新线程？
Yes there's all kinds of possible solutions here,
是的，这里有各种可能的解决方案，
just like warning you that you know there's alerting you
我只是在警告你，在提醒你，
that you have to think a little bit about how you arrange this.
你必须考虑一下如何安排这件事。
Okay?
好的？
But isn't isn't it using a single thread not sufficient,
但是，使用单个线程是不是不够，
because the thread that puts it onto the apply channel,
因为放入 apply 通道的线程，
will still be looking at data, right,
会继续关注数据，
so it still need to acquire the lock.
所以它仍然需要获得锁。
Okay, Okay, let me get back on here,
好的，让我回到这里，
it's easy to see that the deadlock here, correct,
很容易看出，这里的死锁，
like if you're in the apply channel,
如果你在 apply 通道，
you're not reading from the apply channel,
你不是在读取 apply 通道，
because you're using your calling start,
因为你在调用 Start ，
like maybe I get because,
我可能会得到，
and start can't run because the guy actually holds a lock,
而 Start 不能运行，因为这个持有一把锁，
but he can't actually unlock,
但它不能解锁，
because he can't write to apply channel,
因为它不能写入 apply 通道，
because there's no reader you know there's easy to construct scenarios,
因为没有读取者，
where you can get into deadlocks,
在那里你会陷入死锁，
of course you can avoid all these deadlocks,
当然，你可以避免所有这些死锁，
that's the whole goal
这就是我们的目标，
and one way to avoid these deadlocks is
而避免这些死锁的一种方法是，
actually not to hold the lock while read writing on the channel,
不要在读写通道时持有锁，
there are other ways of doing it too,
也有其他方法可以做到这一点，
I just tell you in my implementation,
我只是告诉你在我的实现中，
you know I find a convenient not to have a whole box while writing on a channel,
我发现这很方便
I think in general it's bad practice.
我认为总的来说，这是一种糟糕的做法。
Okay, back to code.
好的，回到代码上来。
Okay good, so I'm gonna show you one particular implementation,
好的，我将向你们展示一个特定的实现，
again, you know this is an implementation that I wrote over January
再次，这是我在一月份编写的一个实现，
to get ready for the class,
为了备课，
so there's nothing particularly special about it,
所以它没有什么特别之处，
you know purely for myself
纯粹是为了我自己，
and I'm sure you know there are things about it,
我相信关于它的一些事情，
that you were to violently object to,
你会强烈反对的东西，
but it gives you a sense you know what I did.
但这给你一种感觉，我做了什么。
And so here I go,
所以我开始了，
so there's the raft structure,
这就是 Raft 结构，
I basically you know copy figure 2,
我从图 2 复制的，
as you will see, in the code,
正如你将看到的，
that's going to be a lot of figure 2 in the code,
在代码中，
and you know here's the main thing you make,
这是你做的主要东西，
probably the main thing to point out,
可能需要指出的主要问题是，
there's like, here's the big mutexes
这是 Mutex ，
and here's the raft lock,
这是 Raft 锁，
that and my code will acquire release all over the place,
我的代码将在所有地方获取释放，
but in a very coarse-grained manner
以一种非常粗粒度的方式，
and the rest is just you know exactly as you expect,
剩下的就是，
you know the Persistent state, Volatile state, Leader state and Snapshot state,
持久性状态，易失性状态，领导者状态和快照状态，
I won't talk much about snapshot at all,
我不会太多地谈论快照，
since you know that what we do for Friday.
因为这是我们周五要做的事。
That's basically it,
基本上就是这样，
then, interesting, I'm just gonna go bottom-up sort of like in the beginning,
然后，有趣的是，我将自下而上，
so at some point the tester,
所以在某种程度上， tester ，
the tester will call Make, right
tester 将调用 Make ，
and here's my basically the Make call,
这是我的 Make 调用，
it constructs you know the raft states,
它构建了 Raft 状态，
you know apply channel, the condition variable that I mentioned,
apply 通道，还有我提到的条件变量，
it sets itself to a follower, it's election time out,
它将自己设置为跟随者，选举时间到了，
and I'll talk about that in a second,
我稍后会谈到这一点，
you know initially some other parts you make an empty log,
一开始，把其他一些部分做成一个空的日志，
and, um, then basically forks have two Go routines,
然后，然后生成两个 goroutine ，
one is the applier, that's the thread that actually writes on the apply channel,
一个是 applier ，这是在 apply 通道上写入的线程，
and then I got my the ticker
然后是一个 ticker ，
and we basically gave you to a basically runs the ticker code,
运行 ticker 代码，
so, nothing particularly exciting going on here.
所以，这里没有什么特别令人兴奋的事情。
So let's look at the ticker code,
那么让我们来看一下 ticker 代码，
some people ask you know, should you structure everything in a single file, multiple files,
有些人问到，
of course it's all up to you,
当然，一切都取决于你，
what actually is most convenient for you
你到底最方便的是什么，
to actually you know find your code,
找到你的代码，
in this case I instructed in multiple files
在这种情况下，我使用多个文件组成，
and have basically vote.go, deals with all the election part.
有 vote.go ，处理所有选择部分。
So let's look at the ticker,
那么让我们来看一下 ticker ，
so the ticker basically runs every 50 milliseconds
所以， ticker 每 50 毫秒运行一次，
and it calls this function tick,
它调用这个函数 tick ，
function tick like right up here,
函数 tick 在这里，
it grips you know you'll see that all over the place,
它获取，
it grasps the raft lock,
它获取 Raft 锁，
calls use defer to make sure that no matter when I leave the function,
使用 defer 来确保无论我何时离开函数，
the lock actually will be released
锁将被释放，
and then you know check what is the leader,
然后检查什么是领导者，
if the leader does one thing,
如果是领导者，做一件事，
it's not a leader, that means that's a follower,
如果它不是领导者，这意味着它是一个跟随者，
then just check whether actually the election time has passed,
那就检查一下选举时间是不是过去了，
and so basically the way I compute that is,
所以我计算的方法是，
I get the current time,
我获取现在的时间，
and see if the current time is actually passed the,
并查看当前时间是否已过，
if now, is now past the election time,
now 是否过了选举时间，
and if that's the case, I'll start the election
如果是这样的话，我将开始选举
and, well first I'll set the election timeout again,
首先，我将再次设置选举超时，
as required by figure 2
如图 2 所示，
and then they'll start the election,
然后开始选举，
in terms of setting the election timeouts,
在设置选举超时方面，
like the the first thing you know the way I do it,
第一件事，我做的方式，
you know an election timeout is set to one second,
选举超时设置为一秒，
which is sort of I got from,
从某种意义上说，我是从，
I can hold on a second [],
稍等一下，
there's a good reason from the chat,
我们的聊天中有一个很好的理由，
the the the selection timeouts one second
选择超时一秒，
and then of course you know you need to randomize you know the peers across an interval,
当然，你需要，
and I use an interval from 0 to 300 milliseconds
我使用的间隔是 0 到 300 毫秒，
and add that to the election timeouts
再加上选举超时时间，
and so basically every peer likely has to have a slightly different election timeout
所以，每个节点会有一个略有不同的选举超时时间，
and so, they will call, take at different stages
所处，它们会调用，在不同的阶段采取行动，
and you know we had a bit of lock,
我们有一点[]，
only one or few actually will start the election.
只有一人或几个会开始选举。
I have a question.
我有个问题。
Yeah.
嗯。
So, you're only like checking every like 50 milliseconds, right,
所以，你每隔 50 毫秒检查一次，
doesn't that lead to a contested elections,
这不会导致一场竞争激烈的选举吗，
like because you're essentially,
就像因为你是，
it doesn't this limit,
它没有这个限制，
like you know you technically can get for anywhere from 3 to 0 to 300 right, like.
从技术上讲，你可以得到任何，
No, I can get from one second to after 300
不，我可以从 1 秒到 300 ，
and one second to any value between 1000 milliseconds to 1300 milliseconds.
一秒到，
Right, so, but at the end of the day,
对，所以，但到了最后，
like because you're like only checking every 50 milliseconds,
因为你每隔 50 毫秒才检查一次，
doesn't that just give it like.
这不是给了。
It gives us more course-grained, but it's good enough.
它为我们提供了更多的粗粒度，但已经足够了。
Okay.
好的。
I mean basically two constraints here, correct,
我的意思是这里有两个限制，
you know you don't want to be too slow
你不想太慢，
and because that means that you're takes a long time before you start a new election,
因为这意味着，
and you don't want to be too fast,
你不想太快，
because then you start too many elections,
因为那样你就会开始太多的选举，
and you need to allow for some time for an election to lose some votes, may get delayed
你需要留出一段时间
and you don't want to restart before you you have,
你不想在之前重启，
just before the candidate has chance to sort of do a couple rounds of communication with the followers.
在候选者改变之前，
Okay, so some of your people speculating about my capital L,
好的，你们一些人在猜测我的大写字母 L ，
this was just an experiment,
这只是一种实践，
you know for this implementation,
对于这个实现，
I followed the convention and I probably broke it in some places,
我遵循了惯例，
but I followed the conception that,
但我遵循的惯例是，
if the caller the [] assumes that the lock is held,
如果调用者，被调用者假设锁被持有，
then I put a capital L behind the function,
然后我在函数后面加一个大写的 L ，
so start election, that assumes that the caller actually is required the lock
所以 startElection 假设调用者持有锁，
and basically any function that [] with an L,
任何带有 L 的函数，
as that particular you know assumes that convention,
假设了这一惯例，
and so this is purely a coding prevention for myself
所以这纯粹是我自己的一种编码预防，
and I thought it was sort of interesting to try it out in this implementation,
我认为在这个实现中尝试它是一件有趣的事情，
might not always do that,
可能并不总是这样，
but I just did that in this one.
但我在这里是这么做的。
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
Or should we look at the election part.
或者我们应该看看选举部分。
Okay, well, let's look at the election part
好的，让我们来看看选举部分，
and you'll see here start election,
你会看到这个 startElection ，
so it doesn't require a lock,
所以它不需要锁，
because I assume the caller holds it,
因为我假调用者持有它，
and basically just follows figure 2,
基本上按照图 2 所示，
you know first, you know the rule is you have to increment the current term by one,
首先，规则是，
so I do that,
所以我就这么做了，
I set the state to Candidate
我把 state 设为 Candidate ，
and also dictated by figure 2 basically,
也是由图 2 指示的，
I [record] voted for myself,
我记录 votedFor 给自己，
this is also part of figure 2,
这也是图 2 的一部分，
and then you know this is for lab c,
然后这是为了实验 C ，
you know to see you already know,
对于 C ，你已经知道了，
that whenever you change basically state, that seemed to be persistent,
每当你改变状态时，都应该持久化，
you have to persistent right after,
你必须在这之后持久化，
and so, so that's it,
所以，就是这样，
and basically you're you see my debugging messages,
你可以看到我的调试信息，
like you know from Jose says, you know I always have the source at the beginning
就像 Jose 所说的，
and this simplifies my life
这简化了我的生活，
and I have a bunch of other sort of,
我还有一堆其他类型的，
I don't have a perl script or python script nicely as Jose,
我没有像 Jose 那样好的 Perl 脚本或 Python 脚本，
but I have a bunch of unique scripts,
但我有一堆 Unix 脚本，
that I used to parse the log, print and process,
我用它来解析日志，打印和处理，
and then we call requestVotesL and requestVotesL right up here,
然后我们调用 requestVotesL ，
and you'll see in a second you know how this is going to work out,
你很快就会看到，这是怎么回事，
but basically it as a [] set,
但是如 Cel 所说，
you know we construct the arguments once you know [up front]
我们预先构建参数，
and let me, so let's look at the RequestVoteArgs arguments
让我来，看看 RequestVoteArgs 参数，
and basically your data here
你在这里的数据，
and you know basically it contains exactly you know what basically figure 2 says,
它包含了图 2 所示的内容，
that you contain the Term, CandidateId, the LastLogIndex, and the LastLogTerm,
包含 Term CandiateId LastLogIndex LastLogTerm ，
and [] and one thing, maybe worth pointing out is,
还有一件事，也许值得指出的是，
I do try to write the string functions,
我尝试编写 String 函数，
that allow Go you know when you're typing %v,
这允许 Go ，当你输入 %v 时，
you know, we'll call that string function on this struct
我们将调用这个结构的 String 函数，
and so that allows you to format, you know the the structure,
这让你可以格式化结构，
the request in a nice way,
（格式化） request ，以一种很好的方式，
and again that helps with me, that helps me processing my log,
再次，这对我有帮助，帮助我处理我的日志，
and so basically every request argument that I have,
所以我的每一个 request 参数，
I print in one standard way
我用一种标准的方式打印，
and again to simplify lock processing.
再次简化日志处理。
Okay, back to starting election,
好的，回到开始选举，
so multiple followers start at the same time,
所以多个跟随者同时开始，
you know they become, one of them is hopefully it starts first,
它们中的一个首先开始，
it becomes candidate
它将成为候选者，
and it does request votes
而且它执行 requestVotesL ，
and here the struct you know the arguments,
在这里的结构参数，
put the currentTerm in here, was going to be one,
把 currentTerm 放在这里，将会是 1 ，
if this is the first time for the election,
如果这是第一次选举，
you know who I am,
我是谁，
and my log lastindex, you know which usually is 0 or 1 whatever,
log.lastindex ，假设是 0 或 1 ，
yeah it's gonna be 0, I guess
我想应该是 0 ，
and then the term in that entry which is term 0,
然后条目中的 Term ，即 term 0 ，
because you know what we're doing correctly,
因为我们在做的，
we're running an election for one
我们正在进行选举，
and we need to show what the previous ones were.
我们需要展示之前的是什么。
Okay.
好的。
So then here, this is my standard way of sending RPCs,
然后在这里，
just go for all the peers, skipping myself, of course,
只是遍历所有节点，
I have to count that I voted for myself,
我算了我投了自己的票，
so I set the number of votes to 1
所以我把票数设为 1 ，
and then I basically fork off a a thread,
然后我启动一个线程，
that basically is gonna do actually the sending the RPC to each individual peer,
这是将 RPC 发送到每个单独的节点，
the first argument is the peer to which the RPC sent,
第一个参数是 RPC 发送到的节点，
they all get the same arguments
它们都得到相同的参数，
and also passing the address of the votes,
并传递 votes 的地址，
you know, so they can have a shared vote count.
这样它们可以有一个共同的计票。
Any questions about this?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
So for request votes, the the lock is being held
所以，对于 requestVote ，锁被持有，
and then you're sending the.
然后你会发送。
Yeah, so.
是的，所以。
RPC.
RPC 。
Yeah, so in a request vote here, is the lock actually held inside of this function.
是的，在这里的 requestVote 中，
No, right, because it's a new thread.
不，因为这是一个新线程。
Yeah,new thread, it doesn't hold a lock,
是的，新的线程，它没有持有锁，
and you see my naming convention hinted that,
看我的命名惯例暗示，
because it doesn't have an L there.
因为那里没有 L 。
Okay.
好的。
So really requestVote and the requestVote when actually it starts running,
所以， requestVote ，
it has no locks,
它没有锁，
because only the parent held the lock
因为只有父线程持有锁，
and this guy this thread actually hasn't required the lock yet,
而这个线程没有持有锁，
it does not have lock.
它没有锁。
So, so basically one thread runs for each of these requestVote for each peer,
所以，每个节点的每个 requestVote 都运行一个线程，
it allocates a reply structure,
它分配一个 reply 结构，
and then basically it sends off you know the RPC
然后它发出 RPC ，
and this is all done without holding the lock,
这一切都是在没有持有锁的情况下完成的，
and then, at some point we get a response back
然后，在某个时刻，我们得到了回复，
and then at that point, in response handler,
然后在那个时候，在响应处理程序中，
I grab the log right at the beginning
我从从日志的开始获取，
and do whatever response handling that is necessary.
并执行任何必要的响应处理。
Yeah, go ahead.
好的，继续。
Alright, you said earlier,
好的，你之前说过，
that you shouldn't hold a lock,
你不应该持有锁，
when you're doing like you're doing RPC call,
当你执行 RPC 调用时，
you mean like basically it's okay to,
你的意思是它是可以的，
it's okay for the RPC call itself
对于 RPC 调用本身来说是可以的，
in the RPC called to do, to hold a lock,
在 RPC 调用持有锁，
but not like while you're calling.
但不是你在调用的时候。
Yeah, I'm not a cross this,
是的，不是在这里，
why are you sitting a cross sending it over the network.
当你通过网络发送它时。
But it's okay, if you're doing it within RPC.
但是，如果你是在 RPC 内完成的，这是可以的。
Or even the reply handler,
或者甚至回复处理程序，
like think about this as ways we reply handler running,
考虑这个是回复处理程序运行，
so the response came back
所以回复回来，
and now there's a reply, you have to process the reply.
现在有了回复，你必须处理回复。
Oh, I'm talking about like say in the request,
哦，我是说，在 RequestVote 中，
but like the capital R requests, capital V vote,
大些的 R request ，大写的 V vote ，
that's okay to hold locks, in there at least right.
持有锁是可以的，至少在那里。
Where you want to hold locks, I'm actually.
你想持有锁的地方是哪里？
Like, so like capital RequestVote here, yeah,
大写的 RequestVote ，
This one?
这个？
No, like the function here,
不，是这里的函数，
so it's request vote,
它是 RequestVote ，
but it's I think it's capital R, yeah,
但是我想它是大写的 R ，
like you probably have a method, right,
你可能有一个方法，
it's the RPC call.
是 RPC 调用。
I think the RPC on the receiver side.
我认为是接收方的 RPC 。
Yeah yeah yeah, we'll look at the second of course,
是的，我们稍后当然会看到，
that was on a completely new way to think about it,
这是一种全新的思考方式，
totally different machine, yeah yeah yeah, absolutely.
完全不同的机器，
So, so basically these two places of our whole block,
所以，这里有两个地方持有锁，
like in the handler in the request handler and in the reply handler.
例如在请求处理程序中和在回复处理程序中。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Sorry, sorry for being confused,
抱歉，抱歉弄糊涂了，
I'm glad we clarified that.
我很高兴我们澄清了这一点。
Okay, so grab block then put a print statement in the log,
好的，所以持有锁，
so I can know what later on I can study it
这样我以后我可以研究它，
and then of course the basic checks,
当然，还有基本的检查，
you know that you know you actually figure 2 different from saying much about it,
图 2 没有说太多，
but you know this is the rule that applies to all servers correct,
但这是适用于所有服务器的规则，
the term is bigger than the reply terms,
term 比 reply.Term 大，
better than the current term,
比 currentTerm ，
then you gotta switch to the follower state
然后你必须切换到跟随者状态，
and to the term of the person that responded to you,
对于回复你的 term ，
so look at that in a second.
我们马上就能看到这一点。
So that basically you know if this this was the candidate
所以如果这是候选者，
and I was talking to appear that actually works in the higher term
出现更到的 term ，
and basically backs off and becomes a follower.
就是后退，成为一个跟随者。
Okay, so, if the follower responded saying,
好的，所以，如果跟随者回答说，
I'm grabbing my vote,
我投票，
then I increment the number of votes, the self vote by 1,
然后我增加共享的 votes 加 1 ，
it is totally safe to do correctly,
这完全是安全的，
because I'm holding the raft lock
因为我持有 Raft 锁，
and so this is a serialized,
所以这是一个串行的，
so multiple things that will happen correct,
所以会有很多事情发生，
multiple responses will come back,
会有多个回复，
they may run in parallel,
它们可以并行运行，
but they won't be serialized,
但它们会串行化，
because of the raft lock,
因为 Raft 锁，
so add up the votes,
所以把选票加起来，
if the vote is longer than the
如果投票超过，
you know if I have a majority of the votes,
如果我拥有多数选票，
then if I'm still in the same term as the start,
如果我还在和开始一样的 term ，
when I started out actually running the election,
当我开始选举时，
then I'm going to become the leader
然后我就会成为领导者，
and I'll send out you know the first round of heartbeats,
我会发出第一轮心跳，
which all look in a second.
我们稍后会看到。
Yeah, so I want to look at two things,
是的，所以我想看两件事，
let's see what become leader is,
让我们看看 becomeLeaderL 是什么，
become leader is right up here,
becomeLeaderL 就在这里，
you know as capital L,
大写的 L ，
because it's you know already holds a lock,
因为它已经持有锁，
basically sets the state to the leader state,
将状态设置为领导者状态，
and initialize is the next index,
并且初始化 nextIndex ，
and the next index or simply the last lecture is basically guess
nextIndex 上节课说的，是一个猜测，
and it's an optimistic guess,
这是一个乐观的猜测，
you know I just said to whatever my last index plus 1,
我的 lastindex 加 1 ，
so basically assuming that all the followers are up to date,
所以假设所有的跟随者都是最新的，
and if they're not,
如果它们不是，
you know we'll see later they will back off,
我们以后会看到它们会回退，
okay, I'll back off on the append entry, sorry by reply.
会放弃附加条目，并重试。
Okay good,
好的，很好，
so that has become leader,
所以，它已经成为了领导者，
let me look at newTermL,
让我看看 newTermL ，
so newTermL, nothing really, you know too exciting
所以 newTermL 没有什么很兴奋的东西，
and basically says I can go to the next term,
就是说我可以进入下个 term ，
that is supplied by the caller,
它由调用者提供，
I set votedFor to -1,
我将 votedFor 设置为 -1 ，
because I haven't voted yet in this term,
因为我在这个 term 还没有投票，
and I changed to a my state to follower,
我把状态改成了跟随者，
because this is kind of state that needs to be persisted,
因为这是一种需要持久化的状态，
I call persist.
我调用 persist 。
Okay, so this is sort of the candidate side
好的，这就是候选者一方，
and now we want to look at follower side,
现在我们想看看跟随者一方，
or perhaps another candidate, that's also running election in parallel.
或者可能是另一位候选者，也在并行运行选举。
So, so here's the RequestVote handler,
所以，这是 RequestVote 处理程序，
this is running,
这是在运行，
so this is the piece of code that runs on the other machine,
这是在另一台机器上运行的代码，
if you will, correct,
如果你愿意，
were where I was confused about a little bit in answering that question
我在回答这个问题时有一点困惑，
and you know you succeeded the first thing it does
你成功的第一件事是，
is vote by the RPC library system, correct,
由 RPC 库系统投票，
with its own thread
有它自己的线程，
and the first thing it does it actually wraps the lock on the raft structure,
它做的第一件事是，
and then basically this follows literally the rules figure 2,
这基本上遵循了图 2 所示的规则，
you know there's the rule for all servers correct,
这些规则是对所有服务器的，
if the term, the argument the term argument is higher than my current term,
如果 args.Term 大于 currentTerm ，
then I should switch you know to this new term
那么我应该切换到这个 newTerm ，
and that's it,
仅此而已，
then here, sort of the you know the interesting piece correct,
然后在这里，有趣的部分是，
this is all related to figure [],
这都与图[]有关，
what it means to be worth about [] figure 7,
它的意思是[]图 7 ，
what it means to be up to date,
它的意思是最新的，
you can only become a leader, if you're up to date,
你能成为一名领导者，如果你是最新的，
so I compute you know the uptodate function,
所以我计算 uptodate 函数，
in and that's basically based on the last index or in the term in the last index,
它基于 last index 或 last index 中的 term ，
and so it says uptodate is,
所以它说 uptodate 是，
if my term in the argument is equal to my term
如果参数中的 term 等于 myTerm ，
and the the caller, the caller the candidate as a LastLogIndex that just equal or higher to myIndex,
调用候选者，
so basically to turn to equal the longest log should win
所以，等于最长的日志的 term 会获胜，
and or if you know the candidates in higher than term period,
或者如果候选者高于 term ，
then it always wins, the candidate wins.
那么它总是赢，候选者就赢了。
So that means it to be up to date,
这意味着它必须是最新的，
so compute uptodate
因此计算 uptodate ，
and then basically go through different cases,
然后通过不同的情况，
if the term is smaller than the current term,
如果 term 小于 currentTerm ，
that means that the caller is behind
这意味着调用者落后了，
and so I VoteGranted to false
所以 VoteGranted 为 false ，
and then in the other case,
然后在另一种情况下，
if I hadn't voted,
如果我没有投票，
or I voted you know already voted for this candidate,
或者我已经投给这个候选人，
and you know the candidate is uptodate,
而且候选者是最新的，
then I grant my vote
那么我同意我的投票，
and and reset the election timeout,
并重置选举超时，
so why, why is this the second case here,
那么为什么这里的第二个情况，
the or are votedFor is args CandidateId.
或者 votedFor 等于 args.CandidateId 。
Because the, the candidate may resend, maybe their RPC was delayed.
因为，候选者可能会重发，可能它们的 RPC 延迟了。
Yeah delayed or actually never made it right.
是的，推迟了，或者从来没有做过。
And so, you know just basically checking,
所以，基本上就是检查，
so this allows me to vote twice for the same candidate,
这允许我为同一候选人投两次票，
but I can't vote for any other candidate.
但我不能投票给任何其他候选人。
Okay?
好的？
So just to double check the logic here,
所以为了再检查一下这里的逻辑，
so if we have the candidate has a term,
如果候选者有一个 term ，
that is bigger than the current term,
它比 currentTerm 大，
we obviously have to convert the follower
显然，我们必须转为跟随者，
and update the term to the term of the candidate,
并更新 term 到候选者的 term ，
but we don't automatically grant them vote,
但我们不会自动授予它们投票，
unless their log is at least as up to date.
除非他们的日志至少是最新的。
Yeah, exactly.
是的，就是这样。
Awesome, thank you.
太棒了，谢谢。
I'm also wondering is voted for every reset to -1.
我还想知道，每次 votedFor 都重置为 -1 ？
Yeah, when we go to new term, always,
是的，当我们进入 newTermL 的时候，总是，
it's new said always to,
它总是，
whenever you go to the new term.
每当你进入 newTermL 时。
Okay.
好的。
I set to -1, is one place where this happens.
我设置为 -1 ，这是发生这种情况的地方。
Any questions?
还有什么问题吗？
So this gives you probably a reasonable good sense about the overall structure
所以，这可能会给你整个结构有一个相当好的感觉，
and this is what everything else follows roughly the same structure.
这就是其他一切都遵循大致相同的结构。
And so let's go back and go here,
所以让我们回到这里，
so let's you know let's assume that guy actually the leader where the candidate wins the election.
所以，让我们，
So it started the election,
所以它 startElectionL ，
let me go trace back,
让我回溯一下，
so we started the election,
所以我们 startElectionL ，
we requested the votes
我们 requestVotesL ，
and we won the election,
我们赢得了选举，
and we became the leader
我们成了领导者，
and then the first thing that figure 2 tells you to do is
然后图 2 告诉你要做的第一件事是，
like send heartbeats to every peer,
向每个节点发送心跳，
and so basically this is going to be the standard code for sendAppendsL.
这是标准的代码 sendAppendsL ，
In fact you know the heartbeat code is identical to the sendAppendsL entry code,
事实上，心跳代码与 sendAppendsL 代码相同，
except you know the heartbeat often will may have no entry
除了心跳常常会没有条目，
or no entry in the log that is being sent to the followers.
或者在发送给跟随者的日志中没有条目。
Okay, so sendAppendsL follows the same structure as in votes,
好的，所以 sendAppendsL 与 sendVotesL 的结构相同，
you know go cycle overall peers,
循环节点，
and if peers not equal to me,
如果节点不等于我，
then basically send it to appends.
然后 sendAppendL 。
Yeah, and so here's to sendAppendL,
是的，所以这是 sendAppendL ，
and, you know basically we're keeping track correct what did the next a log entry,
而且我们跟踪的是，
that the peer should have,
这个节点应该有的，
we initialize it to an optimistic guest in equal to [],
我们将其初始化乐观猜测等于我们的，
so basically in this case, there's gonna be no log entries,
所以，在这种情况下，
so I can skip all this stuff for now,
所以我现在可以跳过所有这些东西，
we'll come back to it, when we're looking actually at start,
我们会回到这里，
I fill in the AppendEntriesArgs,
我填入 AppendEntriesArgs ，
and we can look at the structure,
我们可以看看它的结构，
you would like to,
如果你愿意，
but you know it is exactly as in figure 2,
但它和图 2 完全一样，
may be the only thing that'll be careful,
可能是唯一要小心的事，
you've got to be a little careful about is
你要小心的是，
allocated slice, you know to hold the entries that need to be sent,
分配切片保存需要发送的条目，
in this particular case, number of entries zero,
在这种情况下，条目数量为零，
were x because we're assuming that everybody's up to date
因为我们假设每个都是最新的，
and then copy you know the part from the slices from the log in the raft structure
然后复制日志的切片部分到 Raft 结构，
to the, to the entries in the arguments,
到参数中的条目，
and so I have really my own copy at this point of the log,
所以我在这一点上，有自己日志的复制，
there's a little bit of danger, correct,
有一点危险，
like slice share memory,
分片共享内存，
so this is why the copy needs to happen,
这就是复制需要发生的原因，
so I copied entries out of the raft structure,
所以我从 Raft 结构复制出条目，
that I hold the log on into my private argument structure,
我把日志保存在我的私有参数结构中，
and, once that is done,
而且，一旦完成了，
basically I sent you know started Go function, Go Go routine for every peer
我为每个节点启动一个 goroutine ，
and in that Go function,
在那个 Go 函数中，
in that and in that function, I sent the RPC
在那个函数中，我发送了 RPC ，
and then in the reply handler,
然后在回复处理程序中，
I grab the log,
我获取锁，
just reply handler of RPC,
只需 RPC 的回复处理程序，
grab the log and then process the reply,
获取锁，然后处理回复，
the append reply.
追加答复。
Does this all make sense?
这能理解吗？
But.
是的，继续，也许一个接一个。
One little question, yeah, so in sendAppendL,
一个小问题，所以在 sendAppendL 中，
we have, we have the loop in which we call rf.sendAppendL,
我们有循环，
and we assume the lock is held through that call,
我们假设锁是在调用过程中持有的，
but we do there you know any thread,
但我们在任何线程，
at which point a thread, let's go to the lock, right.
在某一点上，线程会获取锁，对吗？
Okay, so like there's an outer loop, correct,
好的，这里有一个外部循环，
where somebody to caller holds the lock
调用这持有锁，
and basically it calls sendAppendL you know n times,
它调用 sendAppendL n 次，
where n is the number of peers minus 1,
其中 n 是节点的数量减去 1 ，
and for every one of them,
对于它们中的每一个，
for every iteration of the loop,
对于循环的每次迭代，
we're going to create a new go function,
我们将创建一个新的 Go 函数，
that go function runs without holding the locks, right,
那个 Go 函数运行不需要持有锁，
so it will send its RPC without holding locks
所以，它发送 RPC 不持有锁，
and at the same time, the new Go function might be started by the caller,
同时，新的 Go 函数可能由调用者启动，
that actually also is going to send RPC,
它也会发送 RPC ，
although they're sent RPCs go parallel to the followers,
尽管它们发送 RPC 并行到跟随者，
the followers respond,
跟随者回应说，
and all the responses come back in,
所有的回复都回来了，
that will, so that will return, when the following response comes in,
所以它会返回，
that returns from send RPC
从发送 RPC 返回，
and at that point I'll grab the lock to process to reply,
在这一点上，获取锁来处理回复，
now, if the caller still busy sending RPCs to new followers,
现在，如果调用者仍然忙于向新跟随者发送 RPC ，
then basically you know the reply handler will block
那么回复处理程序将会阻塞，
until the caller is done, sending all the RPCs.
直到调用者完成，发送所有 RPC 。
Yeah, so, my question was,
是的，所以，我的问题是，
I I assumed why that happens is,
我假设这会发生的原因是，
because you had a we had a defer rf.lock and the unlock,
因为我们有一个 defer rf.Unlock ，
is that's why it doesn't hold the lock,
这是不是它不持有锁，
when it starts a thread, right,
当它启动一个线程时，
or is that just.
或者这只是。
When you start a thread,
当你启动一个线程时，
you don't hold any locks.
你没有持有任何锁。
Yeah, like whatever it is,
是的，不管是什么，
even if we don't have like that,
即使我们没有，
like even if we tried to hold the lock right,
即使我们试着在 Go 代码之前持有锁，
That's right, yeah yeah.
是的，是的。
Yeah.
好的。
I will sort of follow,
我是跟进，
so in the if ok block,
如果 ok 阻塞，
where's the defer being like called from,
defer 是从哪里调用的，
from the return statement of that method.
从该方法的 return 语句。
When this block exits, when this block exits,
当这个块退出时，
then the defer mu.unlock will be called.
将调用 defer mu.Unlock 。
So defer defer is called when the surrounding basic block exits.
所以， defer 是在包围的块退出时调用。
Oh not just return statements.
哦，不只是返回语句。
Not just return statements, that's correct.
不仅是返回语句，没错。
Okay cool.
好的，酷。
That's cool, it's very handy.
那很酷，非常方便。
Can you repeat that,
你能重复一遍吗，
so what does the defer exists.
defer 什么时候退出？
defer called like when this defer or this unlock runs when this basic block exits
这个 defer 这个 unlock 在这个块退出时运行，
or returns or goes out whatever [] went around,
或返回或退出包围的块，
so if you return from this basic block,
所以如果你从这个块返回，
this unlock will happen.
这个 unlock 将会发生。
That's awesome.
那真是太棒了。
Sorry, why, you need to check if the current term is still the term that you thought you were in,
抱歉，为什么，你需要检查，
because some requests can be slow
因为有些请求可能会很慢，
and you might receive a response now after a long time.
你可能会在很长一段时间后收到回复。
Yep.
是的。
Okay.
好的。
So here's all let's look at process and reply,
所以，我们看一下 processAppendReply ，
I think that's what you're asking what does it do,
我想这就是你在问它是做什么的，
and we have looked at it yet,
我们已经看过了，
so we can look at it,
这样我们可以看到它，
actually reasonable complicated,
实际上相当复杂，
it follows you know the general rule for all servers,
它遵循所有服务器的一般规则，
you have the required terms beginning my current term,
你有 reply.Term 大于 currentTerm ，
then you know I got switched to becoming a follower
然后我变为一个跟随者，
and you know going to a new term,
然后去 newTermL ，
if it is actually equal to my term, correct,
如果它等于我的 term ，
this is what you are asking,
这就是你要问的，
like if the reply comes in the same term,
如果回复是在同一个 term 内，
that I sent in my args term,
我发送了 args.Term ，
then I'm gonna do a have a different function,
然后我要做一个不同的函数，
that actually does all the processing,
它完成了所有的处理，
assuming that at least the terms are matching.
假设至少这些 term 是匹配的。
Oh, sorry, I meant in the leader,
哦，抱歉，我是说在领导者里，
when receives a response you have,
当收到回复时，
it had like a check.
它需要检查。
Yeah, yeah basically happening here too,
是的，是的，也在这里发生，
it's like the same check here.
这里有同样的检查。
I see, okay.
我明白了，好的。
Okay, so you know basically this is then the append entries, reply code,
好的，这就是附加条目，回复代码，
like what the handler that runs in response to the reply,
比如响应回复的处理程序，
we know that the term matches and we check reply success,
我们知道 term 匹配并且我们检查回复成功，
if reply success you know we update our match indexes and next index,
如果回复成功，
follow exactly the rules of figure 2,
完全遵循图 2 的规则，
if there's a conflict valid,
如果有 ConflitValid ，
you know then you know I process the conflict
然后我处理冲突，
and so this is the piece of code is going to deal with like backing off fast.
这是一段要处理的快速回退的代码，
And, and if there's no conflict information available,
如果没有可用的冲突信息，
then I just back off by one.
然后我就退一步。
Okay?
好的？
Is it a question about how we back off by one,
这是一个关于我们如何后退一步的问题，
is it not problem that,
这难道不是问题吗，
I was thinking about this
我在想这件事，
and I I think it wasn't true,
我觉得这不是真的，
but I haven't fully convinced myself,
但我还没有完全说服自己，
but isn't it possible that rf.nextIndex peer changed,
但有没有可能 rf.nextIndex 节点发生了更改，
between when we sent it
在我们发送它的时候，
and when we're processing this response,
当我们处理这些回应时，
you're not problematic, the document kind of using a value that's potentially changed.
你会有问题，
Probably not, great,
可能不会，
because you think your risk your concern is valid,
因为你的担心是合理的，
because certainly you know the raft structure might have completely changed
因为 Raft 结构可能已经完全改变了，
by the time this response comes in.
等恢复进入时。
In fact, you know although unlikely of course,
事实上，虽然不太可能，
because the response to the same peer right.
因为回复是对同一个节点。
And so there's a you know,
所以有一个，
but I might have multiple RPC outstanding to that particular peer
但是对于那个节点，我可能有多个未完成的 RPC ，
and so those reply handlers here might run in some order.
所以，这些回复处理程序可能会以某种顺序运行。
So I have a question,
所以我有一个问题，
so why do we decrement the nextIndex by 1,
为什么我们要将 nextIndex 减 1 ，
if there's no conflict.
如果没有冲突的话。
I think this has to do that,
我认为这个必须做到这一点，
maybe at some point, I haven't implemented conflict or the conflict term stuff yet,
也许在某种程度上，
I I don't remember whether this action is essential or not.
我不记得这个是不是必须的。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
You know, of course like you I've changed my code multiple times
当然像你一样，我多次更改了我的代码，
and you know as I go along implementing the response of the test,
当我继续实现测试的回复时，
I don't think there's harm in it,
我不认为这有什么坏处，
the only downside could be that I may send too many entries on RPC
唯一的缺点可能是，
or send more entries in the RPC I really have to,
或者在 RPC 中发送更多条目，
on the next append.
在下一个附加上。
Okay, any questions?
好的，还有什么问题吗？
Good, let me talk a little bit about the commit,
好的，让我简单地谈一下提交，
so we might have learned correct that the follower actually has, has committed some entries,
所以你可能已经知道，
that we didn't know before
我们之前不知道的，
and the matchIndex is updated
并且 matchIndex 已经更新，
and so, so basically I always check after processing reply,
所以，我总是在处理回复后检查，
whether I should advance you know the commit point,
我是不是应该提出提交点，
and this is basically the,
这基本上就是，
you know the this code corresponds to the last [] of the leaders in figure 2,
这个代码对应于图 2 中的最后一个领导者[]，
so and literally implement what actually is supposed to be happening there.
实现应该在那里发生的事情。
Probably the only thing that's sort of interesting in here is this particular point,
可能这里唯一有趣的是这个的点，
and this has to do with figure 8, right,
这与图 8 有关，
the scenario is that you're a leader,
场景是，你是一个领导者，
is not allowed to commit a previous term unless at least has committed one entry in its current term,
不允许提交前一个 term ，
and so this is exactly that one check that described section 5.4,
这就是第 5.4 节描述的那个检查，
it checks whether the current log entry,
它检查当前的 log.entry ，
that I want about to be in the entry about to commit,
不会出现在要提交的条目里，
whether that actually has a term is different than the current term
它是否有一个 term 与 currentTerm 不同，
and if that's the case I'll just skip it.
如果是这样的话，我就跳过它。
Now happens if there's another log entry following that term,
现在，如果那个 term 后面有另一个日志条目，
in my term for which I have a majority of the votes,
在我的 term 中，我有投票的大多数，
then I'll basically commit that newer one
那么我会提交新的那个，
and then automatically logs will commit the previous one.
然后自动允许提交前一个。
So that's that figure 8 problem
这就是图 8 的问题，
and then a signalApplierL,
然后是 signalApplierL ，
and the applier you know may run,
applier 可能会运行，
if there's actually a,
如果这里有一个，
let's look at the applier thread,
让我们来看看 applier 线程，
here's the applyer thread,
这是 applier 线程，
signalApplierL for it to wake it up
signalApplierL 用于唤醒它，
when maybe advance the commit point,
当可能提出提交点时，
it has a lastApplied, first grasp a lock, lastApplied,
它有一个 lastApplied ，
and then you basically go through here
然后从这里经过，
and a [dust] to check you know that's the rule for all servers,
执行一个检查对所有的服务器的规则，
you know when you commit something
当你提交一些时，
and it just follows that rule
它遵循这条规则，
and then basically write something to the apply channel
然后向 apply 通道写入一些内容，
and as you can see here,
正如你在这里看到的，
I unlock before writing to the apply channel,
我解锁，在写入 apply 通道之前，
and then, if there's nothing anymore to, nothing more to supply
然后，如果没有更多的东西可以供应，
and this on the apply channel,
在这个 apply 通道上，
I just do a Wait on the condition variable.
我只是在条件变量上等待。
And again, you know different ways of writing this,
再说一次，有不同的方式编写这个，
but this is the way I happened to do it.
但这是我使用的方式。
So why are you using a broadcast?
你为什么用 broadcast 呢？
Oh, why, instead of signal, yeah, no no good reason.
哦，为什么，替换信号，是的，没有充分的理由。
Okay.
好的。
You know broadcast signal in this case do exactly the same thing.
broadcast 信号在这种情况下做的是完全相同的事情。
For the applier.
对于 applier 吗？
Yeah.
是的。
So I using a condition variable
所以我使用了一个条件变量，
and it seems like like probably natural to do that,
这似乎是很自然的事情，
is there any disadvantage to doing it
做这件事有什么坏处吗，
on on like on sleeping, like sleeping for a time interval,
比如睡眠一段时间，
then like you know watching everything together.
然后，一起观察所有东西。
I I I dislike code with random sleeps in them,
我不喜欢随机睡眠的代码，
I think it was generally a bad style of writing code,
我认为这是一种糟糕的代码编写风格，
and so I don't do that.
所以我不会那么做。
Yeah.
嗯。
The only place where I do sleep is in the ticker,
我唯一使用睡眠的地方是在 ticker 中，
that's it,
就这样,
that's the way place where you have to do,
这是你必须要做的事，
so otherwise I just never do that.
否则我永远不会那么做。
Actually, that's is there any advantage to doing it with a ticker?
用 ticker 做，有什么好处吗？
Sorry.
抱歉？
Is there any disadvantage of checking and updating like alongside with the ticker,
与 ticker 一起检查和更新有什么处吗，
like you have.
就像你有。
You could do that I I find it harder to reason about,
你可以这么做，我觉得这很难解释，
I I'd like to you know if one thread we charged this one thing
如果一个线程[]一件事，
and then the ticker thread in one thing,
然后 ticker 线程一件事，
you know I think there are people that basically do everything in a ticker thread,
我认为有些人所有事情都在 ticker 线程上做，
and you know one of you know for me it's hard to reason about,
对我来说这是很难解释的，
but that's more a question of personal taste than anything.
但这更多的是个人品味问题，而不是任何事情。
Okay?
好的？
Any further questions?
还有什么问题吗？
Okay, I want to quickly look then at start,
好的，我想快速看一下开始部分，
because basically there's nothing really left to discuss anymore,
因为已经没有什可讨论的了，
we talk basically about voting,
我们讨论了投票，
we talked about appending,
我们谈到了追加，
haven't really discussed exactly what happens on the follower side,
还没有讨论过跟随者一方到底会发生什么，
when it gets in appending request,
当它进入附加请求时，
but basically follows figure 2,
但是遵循图 2 ，
if we have time left and we can look at that too.
如果我们还有时间，我们也可以看看这个。
Here's the Start command,
这是 Start 命令，
so this is like the service calls this to append or an entry to the log
这是调用追加条目到日志的服务，
and you know immediately grabs the log,
获取锁，
check whether we're still the leader,
看看我们是否仍是领导者，
if not we return false,
如果不是，则返回 false ，
otherwise we create an entry
否则，我们将创建一个条目，
and we append it to the log
然后我们将其附加到日志中，
and log has to be persistent, so were persistent,
日志必须是持久化，所以我们 persist ，
and then we send the applies
然后我们 sendAppendsL ，
and this is exactly the same order sendAppends,
这完全一样，
and except in the, unlike in the heartbeats,
除了在心跳中，
you know most likely now it's going to actually send the entry,
现在，它将发送条目，
that is, that just has been appended to the log.
它被附加到日志中。
Okay?
好的？
You noticed, you know that probably many places have this log.lastindex or log that something
你注意到，
and that's because I sort of abstracted the log away into its own structure.
这是因为我在某种程度上将日志抽象为自己的结构。
Here's the log actually as just a log of entries, slice of entries
这里的日志只是条目的日志，条目的切片，
and the index 0
和 index0 ，
and this is really for part 2d,
这是 2D 部分的内容，
where basically you're gonna cut up the beginning of the log,
你要截断日志的开始部分，
this global log
这个全局日志，
and you need to keep track of what the index,
而且你需要跟踪 index ，
you need to keep track of what the indexes of the first entry actually you have recorded in your log.
你需要跟踪第一个条目的索引
And you know to hide most of those details away,
为了隐藏大部分细节，
you know basically have an abstracted way in this file log.go
在这个 log.go 文件中有一个抽象的方式。
and they're basically functions for appending,
它们是用于附加的函数，
you know to get the start of the logging,
获取日志的开始，
to cut the end,
cutend ， cutstart ，
to get the slides out of it to get the last index,
获取它的切片，
you know get the particular entry or get the last entry,
获取指定的 entry 或获取 lastentry ，
and that might be convenient for 2d,
这对 2D 来说可能是方便的，
although there's many other ways of doing it.
尽管有很多其他的方法可以做到这个。
Okay, let me go back for a second to some of the questions that people ask.
好的，让我回顾一下人们问的一些问题。
So, I think hopefully I've answered many of them by now,
所以，我想我到现在为止已经回答了很多问题，
but if not, let me just review quickly go through them,
但如果不是，让我快速回顾一下它们，
so I think we talked quite extensively about the election timeout,
我认为我们就选举超时问题进行了相当广泛的讨论，
you know how to compute it,
如何计算它，
how to check with the timeout is passed.
如何查看超时时间已过。
There a question about always when receiving a message from leader,
有一个问题是，关于总是收到领导者的消息，
you know I only reset when I receive a message from the leader
我只有在收到领导者的信息后才会重置，
that actually using my current term,
使用我的 currentTerm ，
or in my new term,
或者在我的 newTerm ，
if I become a follower,
如果我成为一个跟随者，
not for somebody that's behind in terms of terms.
不会[]一些落后 term 的。
When to send AppendEntries,
什么时候发送 AppendEntries ，
you know the different ways of doing it,
做这件事的不同方式，
you can do it only in the heartbeats,
你可以只在心跳时做，
you know some people have done that,
有些人这样做过，
you can do, so never send anything in start,
所以永远不要在 Start 中发送任何东西，
that's like I showed me I showed in the code,
就像我在代码中展示的，
or sometimes you people do, also do it in the response,
或者有时候人们也会在回复中做，
if for example the followers behind,
如果后面的跟随者，
you know send immediately, the remaining entries,
直接发送剩余的条目，
I don't do that,
我不会那么做，
I never said anything in response,
我从来没有在回复中发送任何东西，
although I had an implementation that does that,
尽管我有一个实现做过，
the risk is that I think you [swamp] the follower in later labs
风险在于，
or in you know test for 2c 2d.
或者在 2C 和 2D 的测试中。
Do in only some people I think just sent our entries only in a heartbeat,
我认为一些人只是在心跳中发送条目，
so that means every you know you're not allowed to send a heartbeat more than ten times a second,
也就是说每一个，
in the rules of the game for the labs,
在实验的游戏规则中，
so that means that you go to sent append entries,
这意味着你可以发送附加条目，
once every you know 100 milliseconds,
每 100 毫秒一次，
or maybe a little bit faster,
或者更快一点，
that maybe run into problems in lab 3,
这可能会在实验 3 遇到问题，
where we actually see if you make fast enough progress,
我们看你是否取得了足够快的进展，
so basically I do it in a heartbeat,
所以我是在心跳完成的，
and I do it in start.
我在 Start 这样做。
We talked quite extensively about debugging,
我们非常广泛地讨论了调试，
talked a bunch about code organization,
谈了很多关于代码组织的话题，
I think we talked quite a bit about concurrency.
我想我们谈了很多关于并发性的问题。
There's a number of questions about why 3 5 7 servers and never more,
有许多问题是关于为什么 3/5/7 台服务器，而不是更多，
I think this is the reason, that is the case,
我想这就是原因，
because I think it reflects how raft is actually used in practice
因为我认为它反映了 Raft 在实践中的使用情况，
and really that 3 5 7 is based on the computation of knowing what the meantime between failures are,
3/5/7 是基于
right, in the raft paper,
在 Raft 论文中，
it's assumed that any time could be failures are rough a couple months,
它推测任何失败大概几个月，
you run with 3 servers,
你使用 3 台服务器运行，
one goes down,
一个停机，
you know you have plenty of time to actually rebuilt you know third server
你有足够的时间来重建第三台服务器，
and get it back online
然后让它重新上线，
and so get back to three before,
所以回到之前的三个，
hopefully the next failure happens,
在下一次失败发生之前，
that's why you know this a small number of servers.
这就是为什么这是少量的服务器。
We talked a little bit about when to persist,
我们讨论了一下什么时候应该持久化，
a number of good questions,
一些很好的问题，
about like what happens if you crash while writing to stable storage,
如果在写入稳定存储时崩溃，会发生什么，
and so you may write partial state and that would be a disaster
所以你可能会写入部分状态，这将是一场灾难，
and so typically what people do is
所以人们通常会做的是，
actually to make sure that when they write to stable storage,
为了确保当它们写入稳定存储时，
that is an atomic operation,
这是一个原子操作，
you know this does show up in the tester,
这会在 tester 中显示出来，
because the tester basically simulates persistent storage
因为 tester 模拟持久性存储，
and then basically updates the persistent storage atomically,
然后原子地更新持久存储，
within a real system that actually has a disk,
在一个真实系统中，有一个磁盘，
you might play a trick, like that produced library did where atomically rename,
你可能会使用一个技巧，
you first write it in temporary file,
你首先将其写入临时文件，
until everything is written and then atomic rename,
直到一切都写好，然后原子重命名，
or use a lot write as logging system,
或者使用一个预先式日志系统，
but yeah you have to, that be a disaster,
但你必须这样做，
if the crash persistent state to stable storage becomes inconsistent.
如果崩溃，到稳定存储的持久化状态变得不一致。
Okay, let me stop here,
好的，让我停在这里，
so like there's maybe a little bit more time to ask questions
所以可能会有更多的时间来提问，
and of course I'll stay around as always,
当然，像往常一样，我会留在这里，
and I can answer more questions,
我可以回答更多的问题，
I see there's also a ton of discussion in the chat,
我看到在聊天中也有大量的讨论，
I'm not I'm unfortunately not able probably I didn't keep up with all of it.
很遗憾可能我没有跟上所有的进度。
Okay good.
好的，很好。
Okay, so yeah any more questions?
好的，还有什么问题吗？
I have a question about the log,
我有一个关于日志的问题，
your your code for the log,
你的日志代码，
the index 0, it is, I guess in the underlying array,
index0 ，它是，
what the start of the log is,
是日志的开头，
is that right?
是这样吗？
So this is basically for lab 2d,
这基本上是实验 2D 的内容，
not for no in lab a b and c
不是，在实验 A B 和 C 中， index0 总是 0 ，
in lab 2d where you take snapshots,
在实验 2D 中，你执行快照，
you know the index 0 with no index number of the snapshot,
index0 没有快照索引号，
because you're gonna be cut the beginning of the log,
因为你会截断日志的开头，
okay, so if you take a snapshot index 10,
如果你把快照索引取为 10 ，
you're gonna cut 0 to 9
你要截断 0 到 9 ，
and index 0 will be 10.
而 index0 将是 10 。
Oh, so this is this is the end of the snapshot,
哦，这是快照的结尾，
I see, okay.
我明白了，好的。
So basically everything through to into index 0
所以任何在 index0 中的东西，
is actually included in the snapshot,
包含在快照中，
so there's no reason to maintain that state anymore in the log.
所以，没有理由再在日志中维护那些状态。
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
I hope this was useful,
我希望这是有用的，
particularly still in time for you know 2c 2d,
尤其是 2C 2D ，
maybe there's some ideas,
也许会有一些想法，
here that might be useful for you in implementing those labs.
可能会对你实现这些实验很有用。
I have a question about like,
我有个问题，
what kind of ranges for election timeouts people used,
人们使用什么样的选举超时范围，
I think I used like you know the the lower the limit of 100 milliseconds for the heartbeats
我想我用了心跳 100 毫秒的下限，
and then timeout anywhere between like 300 and 700 milliseconds.
然后超时时间在 300 到 700 毫秒之间。
Yeah.
嗯。
I don't know if that's.
我不知道，这是不是。
Totally reasonable I usually have a bigger number correctly,
完全合理，我使用了一个更大的数字，
the [range] we gave you is that,
我们给你的[]是，
you know you should be able to elect a leader in 5 seconds,
你应该在 5 秒内选出一位领导者，
and that means you should count on
这意味着你应该指望，
and you may have to run the election a couple times,
而且你可能要运行几次选举，
and so you know the numbers your pick seems reasonable.
所以你选择的数字是合理的。
Any, any people that want to share a particular annoying bug that they had,
任何人想要分享他们有过的恼人的 bug ，
actually a number of questions where people are asking
人们在问的一些问题，
what is the most nasty bug that people have seen.
人们见过的最讨厌的 bug 是什么？
I have a pretty annoying bug in my implementation,
我的实现中有一个非常恼人的 bug ，
I didn't take my own advice
我没有采纳我自己的建议，
and sort of did like weird implantation of a timer
奇怪地实现定时器，
where like spawn off new thread to sleep for something
在那里产生新的线程来睡眠，
and then send a message back at the end,
然后在结尾发回一条消息，
it was not pretty great design,
这并不是一个很好的设计，
and it had two different timers,
它有两个不同的定时器，
one for heartbeats and one for election timers,
一个是心跳，一个是选举计时器，
and I was forgetting to stop the one of those timers,
我忘了停掉其中一个计时器，
when the server shutdown,
当服务器关闭时，
one of them was fine and one of them wasn't
其中一个很好，另一个不太好，
and it meant I would slowly gain like a number of Go routines over the course of a long running test
这意味着很慢[]，
until it ran out
直到它用完了，
and the race detector crashed everything
竞争探测器崩溃了所有东西，
and it was incredibly embarrassing,
这令人难以置信地尴尬，
because it was literally just that I forgot stop the timer,
因为我忘了停止计时器，
so, but it took a very long time to debug,
但是它花了很长的时间来调试，
because I couldn't figure out,
因为我不能解决，
I thought there was a bug in the lab RPC code
我以为实验的 RPC 代码中有 bug ，
and no there wasn't,
不，没有，
no there's probably no bugs in lab RPC code,
不，实验RPC 代码中可能没有错误，
it was just me misinterpreting data.
只是我曲解了数据。
Yep.
是的。
I'm talking about election timeouts,
我说的是选举超时，
I have a issue on where the one call is
我对一个 config.go 中的调用有疑问，
or that were occasionally failed to reach agreement,
或者偶尔不能达成协议，
I realized that, if I increase my election timeouts to have the random interval
我意识到，
go up to 1500 milliseconds,
增加到 1500 毫秒，
like greatly decreases the frequency at which this happens,
大大降低了这种情况发生的频率，
but I'm wondering if I should go even higher than that for the random interval,
但我在想，对于随机间隔，我是否应该比这个更高，
that this is indicative of another bug I have.
这表明我有另一种 bug 。
I think it's indicative another bug you have,
我认为这表明你又有另一个 bug ，
my first guess I got,
我的第一个猜测是，
to know of course I don't know for sure at all,
当然，我也不确定，
but you don't have to be able to run with that kind of long timers to pass.
但你不需要运行这么长时间才能通过。
Yeah, most of the time when people are tweaking their timeouts,
是的，大多数时候，当人们调整他们的超时时，
not actually fixing their bugs,
而不是真正修复它们的 bug ，
it's just changing how often they show up.
它只是改变了它们出现的频率。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
Here's a bug in the channel,
在通道中有一个 bug ，
when the channel was a bug I had,
我有一个 bug 在通道中，
was I forgot to initialize channel,
我忘了初始化通道，
how did how did that manifest itself as a bug.
这是如何表现为一个 bug 的。
Oh, like basically when I was sending something,
哦，当我发送一些东西时，
it wouldn't able to receive it,
它无法接收到它，
and I wondered what was going on,
我想知道发生了什么事，
it turns out it was just that I didn't ever initialize it,
事实证明，只是我从来没有初始化它，
feels like the not nil channel.
就像一个非 nil 频道。
Because I don't really know what the semantics are overwriting to new channel,
因为我不知道新频道的语义覆盖了什么，
I can't recall it top my head,
我想不起来了，
I know the rule for that,
我知道这方面的规则，
but I don't remember what the rule is.
但我不记得规则是什么了。
Do you have a comment on the previous point,
你对前面这一点有什么看法，
regard regarding the election timeout setting them high,
考虑到选举超时，将它们设得很高，
should we try and aim, thus to set them a little bit low,
我们是不是应该试着把它们设置低一点，
so that if there are any bugs, we can expose them.
如果有任何 bug ，我们可以发现它们。
Yeah, not a bad plan,
是的，不是一个坏的方案，
I think it's always good to like,
我觉得总是好的，
you know push the boundaries
推动边界
and see if you have any other bug without working.
看看是不是有其他 bug 。
So the boundary should be something [akin] to what the paper suggests.
所以，边界应该是与论文建议的[类似]的东西。
A little bit higher,
稍微高一点，
because the way we set up the tests are slightly different,
因为我们设置测试的方式略有不同，
you know the intersection of each has a discussion on this, right.
每一个[]都有关于这个的讨论。
And actually the raft paper can pass like guidelines
实际上 Raft 论文可以作为参考，
and even if they have a specific value,
即使它们有特定的值，
they set a value based on the guidelines
他们根据参考设定一个值，
and the guidelines said
参考说，
that you should have elected a leader with an order of magnitude more time
你应该选举一个领导者，
Exactly.
没错。
100 like if you do like 800 to a second,
100 ，如果你 800 到 1 秒，
like things will work out,
事情将会起作用，
it's fine, if those are high,
这是可以的，如果这些都很高，
because that's kind of the guidelines,
因为这是参考，
it all changes, because we just made you change the kind of like the innermost heartbeat frequency,
一切都变了，
because of the RPC [].
因为 RPC[]。
Sorry, can actually see the heartbeat timer in the code?
抱歉，可以在代码中看到心跳计时器吗？
Yeah, sure.
好的，当然。
Basically, you know every 50 milliseconds,
基本上每 50 毫秒，
the ticker goes off,
ticker 走完，
the ticker calls tick
ticker 调用 tick ，
and if a leader obviously send an RPC,
如果一个领导者发送一个 RPC ，
just comes down to basically a heartbeat,
就是一个心跳，
so here, my implementation every 50 milliseconds, I'm sending a heartbeat.
所以这里我的实现，每 50 毫秒发送一个心跳。
Another question,
我有一个问题，
I so, I you were saying like,
你刚才说的，
like, it should be like timeout should be an order of magnitude greater than heartbeats, right,
超时应该
but I started playing to see how low it could get,
但我刚开始看它可以多小，
you know I I could like with 100 millisecond timeout,
我可以使用 100 毫秒超时，
you know it could go down to 3 to 500 milliseconds,
它可能会缩短到 300 到 500 毫秒，仍然有效，
and I was wondering like, it's like why,
我在想，这是为什么，
like how how low you know how low can they get,
它们可以降到多低，
and why are we making them so much greater than the,
为什么我们要让它们变得比，
than the election timeout,
比选举超时，
more than the heartbeat time.
比心跳时间。
Because we need to give the candidate shot actually becoming the leader
因为我们需要给候选人成为领袖的机会，
and some of the messages might be delayed for a long time or dropped.
一些消息可能会被延迟很长时间或被丢弃。
Okay?
好的？
I have a question,
我有个问题，
I think I missed this part,
我想我错过了这一部分，
which is, how you're like which append entries you're sending from start
也就是，
and which ones from the heartbeat,
哪些是来自心跳的。
basically the same, it's the same code.
基本上是一样的，是相同的代码。
Okay.
好的。
Okay, there's nothing difference I only have one,
好的，没什么区别，我只有一个，
if you look here,
如果你看这里，
this guy here sent to appends, right,
这个 sendAppendsL
this is from the ticker.
这是来自 ticker 的。
Yeah.
嗯。
And if you look at the API code,
如果你看一下 API 代码，
start function calls the same function,
Start 函数调用相同的函数，
but in this case which which ones are,
但在这种情况下，哪些是，
like if you're sending all of them from start,
如果把它们全部从 Start 发送出去，
which ones are going to be sent from the ticker.
哪些是从 ticker 发出的。
The ticker probably says mostly empty appends.
ticker 可能更多是空的追加。
Okay, so the both are coming from startd.,
好的，所以这两个都来自 Start ？
No, one is coming from the ticker.
不，一个是从 ticker 的。
Or like the actual log entries.
或者实际的日志条目。
Oh, the oh the actual log entries are all sitting in struct raft, right,
哦，实际的日志条目都在 Raft 结构上，
there coming out of their abstract,
它们来自 Raft 结构，
and if you look at start,
如果你看看 Start ，
the only thing start does,
Start 做的唯一一件事，
hold on, let me go pull up start again,
等一下，我把 Start 找出来，
because it's a good question,
因为这是个好问题，
you pull start basically,
好的，找到 Start ，
it appends to the log here, right,
它会追加到这里的日志中，
and that's all does
这就是所有的事情，
and like the only difference basically between the ticker and start is,
ticker 和 Start 之间唯一的区别是，
that start actually appends something to the log
Start 追加一些东西到日志中，
and the ticker doesn't do that,
而 ticker 没有这么做，
and send appends basically grabs whatever,
sendAppendsL 获取，
so this is the loop for all of them,
这是它们所有的循环，
so here's to the individual,
所以，这是单独的，
oops,
糟糕，
here's the individual one,
这是单独的一个，
they sent to one peer
它们发送给一个节点，
and it basically grabs the right log entries out of the out of log right here,
它从这里中抓取正确的日志条目，
you're copy it out of the log into the args entries,
把它从日志中复制到 args.Entries ，
and so if it's a heartbeat,
如果是心跳，
most likely there's always be 0, not always, correct,
最有可能的是总是有 0 ，但不总是，
because you might be the leader, might be follower, have missed some,
因为你可能是领导者，可能是跟随者，可能错过一些，
but in the case when a start calls this,
但是在 Start 调用这个的情况下，
you always be sending the thing that actually just has been appended.
你总是发送刚刚附加的东西。
Okay, because, I I did it that I such that I'm sending everything in the heartbeats,
好的，因为，
like all the entries,
所有的条目，
and I for some of the two [],
对与某些[]，
sometimes I'll like fail to reach agreement
有时我不能达成协议，
and I'm wondering if that's why,
我想知道这是为什么，
because here it seems like,
因为这里看起来像是，
the bulk of the entries are being sent in start.
大部分条目是在 Start 中发送的。
No, okay,
不，好的，
that might not be the reason why you,
这可能不是你为什么，
I don't think it will affect reaching agreement,
我认为这不会影响达成协议，
is probably not a dependent on the number of entries you send in,
可能并不依赖于你发送的条目数量，
the number of log entries sitting in append RPC.
你在附加 RPC 中发送的日志条目数量。
No.
不是？
Yeah, I was able to make it all the way through lab 2,
是的，我顺利通过了实验 2 ，
with only ever sending append entries from the heartbeat timer,
在仅从心跳定时器发送附加条目的情况下。
things down though.
情况有所好转。
To be clear, I don't recommend doing this,
明确地说，我不建议这么做，
but like, you can get through lab 2,
但是，你可以通过实验 2 ，
with just sending from the heartbeats,
只是从心跳中发送，
so if you're not sure how long the timeout, then.
如果您不确定超时时间有多长，那么。
How do the limits on heartbeats work or the limit on heartbeats,
心跳的限制是如何起作用的，
like the same as limit on append entries RPC
与追加条目 RPC 的限制相同，
or are they counted differently.
或者它们的计算方式不同。
Either in the heartbeat is a bit different,
心跳有一点不同，
you know you can send you know you have to send principle assume,
你可以发送，
that every start can result in an append entry call.
每个 Start 都会导致追加条目调用。
Right.
好的。
And and you're you're not allowed to send more than 10 heartbeats.
你不能发送超过 10 个心跳。
How, how do you, like differentiate that on the test.
你怎么在测试中区分这一点？
Heartbeats have no entries, most typically.
心跳没有条目，最典型的情况是。
Okay, so you literally go in and check like.
好的，所以进去，检查。
Oh, they don't really literally check,
哦，它们不是真的检查，
but we basically see if you make more progress than 10 times a second,
但我们看你是否每秒进展超过 10 次，
like one of the test in lab 3,
比如实验3 中的一项测试，
checks if you go quick enough,
检查你的速度是否足够快，
exactly for this reason,
正是因为这个原因，
maybe a little bit annoying,
可能有点烦人，
but in a real application, correct,
但在实际应用中，
if you delay you know your appends,
如果你延迟你的附加 50 毫秒，
So if a client you imagine a client's meeting to your service,
所以，如果一个客户端访问你的服务，
you know basically it's going to get one append operation through every 50 milliseconds,
它将会，
that would be not a very desirable service to use.
这将不是一项非常可取的服务。
I had a question about accessing parts of the rf struct without lock,
我有一个问题，
so in send append entries,
所以，在 sendAppendEntries ，
you're you're reading the peer, of peers.
你是在读取节点。
Yep.
是的。
Oh I guess slice,
我想切片，
but I know that it is it is static,
但我知道它是静态的，
but there, it could be that multiple threads read the same thing twice, right,
但在那里，
so is, is there a danger of the race the detector complaining about this.
所以，有没有风险，
So let me see,
所以让我想想，
so I guess I don't hold a lock on rf peers, it's not the.
所以我想我没有在 rf.peers 持有锁，这不是。
Yeah.
嗯。
Yeah, maybe race, because there's not complaining,
是的，也许是竞争，因为没有抱怨，
because I always run this race detector.
因为我总是运行竞争探测器。
Sorry, was that question about whether iterating over peers could cause races.
抱歉，你的问题是关于迭代是否会导致竞争吗？
Yeah.
嗯。
Right, just access it without holding the lock.
是的，不持有锁访问它。
Right, there only ever owned, no words, right.
好的，这里只有[] 。
What about rf.killed.
那么 rf.killed 呢？
Sorry.
抱歉？
rf.killed.
rf.killed 。
Oh, I guess it was just an excuse scenario,
哦，我想这只是[]场景，
if you kill it at the same time as doing something else, I'm not sure.
如果你在做其他事情的同时杀死它，
Yeah it says not only modify,
是的，它说的不仅是修改，
killed still doesn't modify peers.
killed 仍然不会修改节点。
Yeah, okay, thank you.
好的，好的，谢谢。
Could I see how you do the apply channel thing again,
我能再看看你是怎么做 apply 通道的吗，
you talked about earlier how you needed to have a lock with the apply channel.
你在前面谈到，
Not unlock, the opposite.
不是解锁，相反。
Oh, sorry, what is it condition variable.
哦，抱歉，这是什么，条件变量？
Yeah, I have a condition variable, yeah.
是的，我有条件变量，是的。
So yeah okay, oh, what do you do with the condition variable though.
所以，好的，哦，你怎么处理条件变量？
I brought a signal on it,
我给它带来了一个信号，
kind of like when, when the matchIndex is updated
当 matchIndex 更新时，
and a new entry needs to be committed
需要提交新的条目，
that thread will call signal,
那个线程将调用信号，
and, that will wake up the apply thread
并且这将唤醒 apply 线程，
and apply thread will see if there's anything that needs to be pushed on the apply channel,
apply 线程将查看，
which is the check here
在这里检查，
and if so, we will put it on the apply channel.
如果是这样，我们将把它放在 apply 通道上。
Oh, okay.
哦，好的。
And if there's nothing to be pushed on your apply channel more,
如果没有更多东西推送到 apply 通道，
it goes back to sleep.
它又回到睡眠状态。
Okay.
好的。
Maybe this is it for today.
也许今天就到此为止。
And who's left.
还有谁还在。